<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The authours, nature, and danger of hæresie. Laid open in a sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons at Margarets Westminster, upon Wednesday the tenth of March, 1646. being set apart as a solemne day of publike humiliation to seeke Gods assistance for the suppressing and preventing of the growth and spreading of errours, heresies, and blasphemies. / By Richard Vines. Printed by order of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E378_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872347</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872347</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 60:E378[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The authours, nature, and danger of hæresie. Laid open in a sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons at Margarets Westminster, upon Wednesday the tenth of March, 1646. being set apart as a solemne day of publike humiliation to seeke Gods assistance for the suppressing and preventing of the growth and spreading of errours, heresies, and blasphemies. / By Richard Vines. Printed by order of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson for Abel Roper, and are to be sold at his shop at the Sun over against Dunstans Church in Fleetstreet.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 2nd, II, 1 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Heresy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Authours, Nature, and Danger OF HAERESIE.</p>
            <p>Laid open in a Sermon Preached before the Honorable Houſe of Commons at <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> upon Wedneſday the Tenth of <hi>March</hi> 1646. being ſet apart as a ſolemne day of Publike Humiliation to ſeeke Gods aſſiſtance for the ſuppreſſing and preventing of the growth and ſpreading of <hi>Errours, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By RICHARD VINES.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heſych.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>There muſt <hi>alſo</hi> be Haereſies. <bibl>1 Cor. 11. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t fides habendo tentationem, haberet probationem. <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertull de praeſcript.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by Order of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Wilſon</hi> for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Sun over againſt <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE Houſe of COMMONS Aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Compaſſe of the ſubject entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon in this Sermon was too large to be ſurveied in a ſhort time. The nature of Haereſy lies under much obſcurity and inevidence. The Infidel who <hi>comes not in</hi> at all, And the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> who <hi>goes out at all</hi> are viſible enough to the eye, but the <hi>Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke</hi> who like a cunning <hi>Bankerupt</hi> breakes with <hi>ſome ſtock</hi> in his hand, and holds ſome <hi>planks of truth when the ſhip is broken,</hi> is more hardly to bee knowne. I have not ſpoken much about the <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of an Haereticke, but rather choſe to ſhew you <hi>who hee is</hi> then <hi>what to doe with him.</hi> There are good rules for the Church her proceeding againſt <hi>ſuch. men,</hi> which may alſo ſerve very fitly to the meridian of your juriſdiction, as namely, <hi>in peccatis eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, in paenis aedificationem;</hi> &amp; againe, <hi>nec cito in apertis, nec unquam in ambiguis,</hi> with many other, which lay on the other ſide of the hedge from my way
<pb facs="tcp:159980:3"/> which was toward the inveſtigation of the <hi>nature of Haereſie,</hi> wherein I hope that what I have offered ſhall be interpreted with candour, for it was not my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſpeake <hi>thunder &amp; lightning,</hi> but to ſpeake to the <hi>enlightning</hi> of the minds of the auditory, and not to the <hi>burning</hi> of <hi>Haereticks</hi> bodies; if any man pleaſe to compare my <hi>language</hi> with that <hi>ſtile</hi> wherein the <hi>holy ſcripture</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>falſe teachers</hi> and their corrupting mens minds, I doubt not but that I ſhall be found <hi>not guilty</hi> of rayling, whereof I have already beene <hi>indited in print,</hi> but I muſt make amends for a long Sermon with a ſhort Epiſtle; and therefore <hi>in a word,</hi> Be quick (Noble Gentlemen) in ſetling the intereſt of Chriſt in this Kingdome. God hath paid you well aforehand, if that doe not ſet an edge upon you, yet be confident that he hath ſomewhat behinde remaining yet in his hand, which he will not part with untill he ſee your worke for him in ſome forwardneſſe, and the longer the yarne hangs in the loome, the more it is ravelled, you have beene told that you have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe in the reformation of the Church, give not the world occaſion to ſuſpect that you thinke ſo too, but goe on with God, and proſper, and the Lord make your way plaine before your face,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So prayes Your moſt humble ſervant in Chriſt Jeſus RICHARD VINES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Houſe of COMMONS at <hi>Margarets Westminſter,</hi> on the tenth of <hi>March</hi> 1646. being a day of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Humiliation for the growth of Errours, Hereſies, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. PETER 2. 1.</bibl>
               <q>But there were falſe Prophets alſo among the People, even as there ſhall be falſe teachers among you, who pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y a Declaration ſet forth above Thirty <note place="margin">His Majeſties declaration in the cauſe of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nradus V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r ſtius</hi> Printed in Engliſh. <hi>Anno</hi> 1612.</note> years ago, King <hi>James</hi> (of Famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory) was pleaſed to let the world know not onely how ill hee reſented, and how much he deteſted the <hi>Vorſtian</hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, then newly borne, and in their ſwadling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloathes:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159980:4"/> but alſo how ſolicitouſly he interpoſed with the <hi>States Generall</hi> of the <hi>Vnited</hi> Provinces againſt their admittance of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>orſtins</hi> into the place of <hi>Divinity</hi> profeſſor at <hi>Leiden,</hi> or into their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; And that he might decline the envy of being <hi>in aliena republica curioſus,</hi> he beares himſelfe upon that common rule <hi>paries cum proximus ardet,</hi> when a neighbours houſe is on fire it concernes all in the neighbourhood to looke about them, this vigilancy condemns our (I know not what to call it, I wiſh no worſe might be ſaid then) inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and ſecurity. For what were thoſe ſparkes at that time ſmoaking in a remote corner in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that fire which now flames forth at every corner of our houſe, blowne up by that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or liberty of all religions, which may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the golden Calfe of theſe times, Where unto many are not unwilling to contribute their ſtrength &amp; pollicy, &amp; whoſe birth-day they would not fear to call <hi>feſtum Jehovae</hi> an acceptable day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord. Are not the errours which are rife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, either by infecting perſons of place and quality growne into that <hi>boldneſſe?</hi> or by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying away <hi>Barnabas alſo</hi> crept into that <hi>credit?</hi> or by ſpreading farre and wide riſen to that <hi>ſtrength?</hi> that they do <hi>face,</hi> if not ſeem able to put into dang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of rowting, our common faith, publike worſhip, authorized miniſtry, long and much expected and promiſed reformation. This to the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is the <hi>Cape</hi> of good hope, the ſound part are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid leaſt the truth ſhould come to begg for poore quarter, and be led Captive following the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of triumphant liberty, ſome thinke that epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159980:4"/> in <hi>his pontificalibus</hi> may by this meanes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, and recalled from exile to which it was ſentenced by the Covenant, many that are as diſtant in their opinions as the two poles, yet moveing up on one axletree, or tyed together by the tayles of Common intereſt, Doubt not but by laying their ſtockes together, they ſhall be able to bid faire for a <hi>Toleration.</hi> And that we might not be left alone to wonder at our ſelves, our ſympathizing brethren abroad do wonder alſo, That we ſhould be made the common ſewre to receive the garbage of other Churches, and that their ſtinking ſnuffes ſhould be allowed candleſticks here in England.</p>
            <p>In this ſad poſture of things, All mens eyes have beene upon the Parliament, and every one ſaith Is there no balme in <hi>Gilead?</hi> is there no Phyſitian there? why then is not the health of the daughter of my people recovered? And the truth is neither your diverſion by ſudden and difficult emergents, nor wiſdom in not diſobliging any party, hath been able to ſatisfie the godly jealouſies of many, untill they eſpied this day breake of hope given to them by your declaration, in which you take notice of a double bond or obligation that lyes upon you.</p>
            <p>1. The firſt is the bond of your ſolemne Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: It will doe very much good abroad when men ſhall ſee that you feele the obligation of that Covenant which ſome do widen into ſuch a latitude of ſence and conſequently into ſuch a looſeneſſe, that they may be eaſily ſaid to keep that which hardly any man can breake; This additionall faſt is an additionall bond alſo. For it cannot be (without further perill to you) both a <hi>faſt</hi> and a <hi>looſe</hi> too.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159980:5"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159980:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159980:6"/> 2. The ſecond is the bond of Gods mercies, <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles rather,</hi> in bringing you cleare out of the fiery furnace and therefore leſſe you cannot doe than <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who being convinced, and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht by the miraculous deliverance of the three ſervants of the Lord, made a decree that none ſhould ſpeake any <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> paraphr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſephi. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> inepti quid.</note> 
               <hi>errour</hi> againſt the God of Shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach Meſhach and Abednego, <hi>becauſe there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God that can deliver after this ſort.</hi> Dan. 3. 29. I crave leave for this prefaceing, It is only to bid this day welcome, becauſe as it is the firſt that ever was in England upon this ſad occaſion, ſo it is a new and ſtrong ingagement and demonſtration of your zeale and reſolution to endeavour, to draine theſe fens which have ſo over ſpread the face of Gods Church.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in the latter end of the foregoing chapter recommends to Chriſtians the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as the fixed pole and un-varying compaſſe by which they ſhould ſteere their courſe, It ſeemes he knew nothing of any ſuch high forme of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Schoole of Chriſt which ſhould (as I may ſay) be got above the Scriptures or have learn'd beyond them. For the commends them who had obtained like pretious faith with himſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of higheſt ranke. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 1. for giving heed to the word of prophecy <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. and as appeares by that expreſſion <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this firſt,</hi> He would have it laid downe as a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and ſet as a ſtrong fort againſt the battery of all falſe teachers <hi>That no prophecy of Scripture is of any private</hi> ſence or <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is the unfolding or cleering of things darke and doubtfull, Mar. 4. 34. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Acts 19. 39. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>interpretation.</hi> becauſe it came not by the <hi>will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159980:6"/> they were carried by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> The ſetling of this principle, and the faſtning of Chriſtians, or as it were nailing them unto the Scriptures; the words of the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, is the ſcope at which the Apoſtle collimes in this Epiſtle, as himſelfe declares, Chap. 3. verſ. 1, 2. &amp; 17. And that it might appeare to them how neceſſary and ſeaſonable it was to ſtirre them up to adhere to the ſure word of God, and the true and genuine ſence thereof, Hee foretells the comming in of Falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Scoffers, <hi>Falſe teachers</hi> that would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the <hi>truth of doctrine,</hi> which is according to godlineſſe, by bringing in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, chap. 2. ver. 1. <hi>Scoffers</hi> that would undermine and elude the <hi>truth of Gods promiſes.</hi> There ſhall come in the laſt dayes Scoffers, walking after their owne luſts, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where is the promiſe of his comming, <hi>Chap. 3. verſ.</hi> 3, 4. And becauſe the Scriptures themſelves were not likely to eſcape the <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Heſych.</hi>
               </note> racke, the Apoſtle gives a double character of ſuch as would crooken it, or make it looke <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sylburg.</hi>
               </note> a ſquint, and they are the <hi>unlearned</hi> and <hi>unſtable,</hi> and ſo concludes with cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all Chriſtians, that they ſhould beware, leſt they being carried away together, by the ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wicked men, or (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) lawleſſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines of opinion and practiſe, fall from their owne ſtedfaſtneſſe, <hi>Chap. 3. verſ.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
            <p>In this Chapter the Apoſtle foretells the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of falſe teachers into the Goſpell Churches, and deſcribes their doctrines, their deſtruction, their manners.</p>
            <p>The doctrines which they teach are damnable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159980:7"/> hereſies, they deny the Lord that bought them.</p>
            <p>Their deſtruction is exemplified and paralleld in three terrible examples, the caſting down of the <hi>Angells that fell,</hi> the deſtruction of the <hi>olde world,</hi> the overthrow of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi> It may make the eares of all haereſie-Maſters and their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to tingle when they heare that the three great and famous monuments of Gods ſore wrath executed by his owne immediate hand are brought in as examples of his vengeance againſt that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which above all other pretends exemption and liberty from the ſtroke of men.</p>
            <p>Their manners (in the deſcription of which the greateſt part of this Chapter is taken up) are drawn out in ſo foule colours, that every man may make the obſervation, That <hi>monſtrous doctrines</hi> are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>monſtrous luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this verſe you have the <hi>ſeedes-men,</hi> and they are falſe teachers; the <hi>ſeed</hi> they ſow, namely dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hereſies. The <hi>crop</hi> they ſhall reap, and that is ſwift deſtruction.</p>
            <p>In the firſt part which ſhewes us the ſeeds-men, there are two points to be taken up.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>That there ſhall be falſe teachers in the Goſpell Churches, as there were falſe Prophets in the Church of olde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>That theſe falſe teachers are they that bring in damnable hereſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſhall be falſe teachers <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> amongſt you in the Churches of the Goſpell, as there were falſe prophets <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> among the people of God of olde. It's ſeldome ſeene that falſe prophets or falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers will owne their owne name: goe from one to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159980:7"/> one and aſke, are you a falſe teacher? and there will not be found any; the confident falſe prophet puts it upon the true Prophet that Hee is the falſe. <hi>Which way went</hi> the Spirit of the Lord from mee to ſpeake to thee? 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 24. which is the falſe prophet we ſhall ſee anon, in the meane time thus farre we are agreed, that there were ſuch then, and that there ſhall bee ſuch amongſt Chriſtians under the Goſpell, though they that are guilty are wiſer than to make ſuch a deſcription of a falſe teacher, or of haereſy which may hit themſelves: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will uſe their ſleight to turne the Scripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as one doth a right hand glove to fit the other hand.</p>
            <p>Falſe Prophets and falſe teachers are paralleld, both in their <hi>being</hi> in the Church, and in their <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> or deſcription.</p>
            <p>1. In their Being in the Church, for</p>
            <p>1. As God then ſent Prophets to teach his people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Jer. 7. 25. Since the day that your Fathers come forth out of the land of Aegypt vnto this day, I have ſent you all my ſervants the Prophets,</hi> and there were then falſe prophets <hi>alſo</hi> ſaith my Text. So <hi>God hath ſet in his Church</hi> under the Goſpell <hi>Teachers,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 28. and there ſhall be <hi>alſo</hi> falſe teachers; then they wore a rough garment to deceive, and now they corne in ſheeps cloathing. The Apoſtle in this <note place="margin">Zech. 13. 4. Matth. 7. 15.</note> Text determines not the falſe Prophets then to a particular place or time, but ſaith they were among the people; nor doth he determine falſe teachers now to any one place or time, but ſpeakes indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, they ſhall be amongſt you. There is no age of the Church free of them: onely the laſt dayes are moſt likely to have moſt of theſe dregs; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159980:8"/> its ſaid of all true Prophets, that they were <hi>ſent,</hi> and of Paſtors and Teachers, that God hath ſet them in, and Chriſt hath given them to his Church; there is no more ſaid of theſe in the Text than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They were,</hi> and <hi>they ſhall be:</hi> they may eaſily find a Propheſie for their being in the Church, but will hardly finde a Scripture-warrant or calling.</p>
            <p>2. As the Church of old, notwithſtanding thoſe living oracles of truth, the holy men of God who ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, and the lively oracles of holy Scripture committed to it, had falſe Prophets alſo, who ſpake their owne dreames: ſo the Goſpell Churches even in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 1. and not withſtanding the fulneſſe and perſpicuity of Evangelicall doctrine given by inſpiration of God, ſhall have falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in them; Who ſhall come up in <hi>Samuels</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and putting the Scriptures to the racke, ſhall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as one ſaith of <hi>Philo</hi>) force things into allegories and conceited extractions, and make them like <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every thing out of any thing. For <hi>an haereticall wit is a ſtrange Chymiſt.</hi> The truth is, the reſiſters of the truth, and the ſeducers in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are but acted over againe in the Goſpell Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Here alſo are the reſiſtings of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres,</hi> by men of <hi>corrupt mindes, reprobate concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 8. Here are the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>Core, Jude.</hi> verſ. 11. Here is the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> Rev. 2. 14. and here are the falſe teachers anſwering to the falſe Prophets, but yet it is argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome that the Analogy betweene the Old and New Teſtament, doth not hold in regard of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159980:8"/> puniſhment of falſe Prophets and blaſphemers, nor ought to be drawn into conſequence now. I would they would rather ſtudy to avoid the ſame ſinnes, then to evade the like puniſhments: for the greater liberty of Conſcience under the Goſpell, cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the ſinne of blaſphemy, becauſe this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is accompanied with greater light.</p>
            <p>2. In their Character or deſcription. The Greek which hath great felicity of compoſition of words calls him in one word a falſe prophet, whom the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew cals a Prophet, &amp; leaves him by ſpurious chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters or properties to be detected falſe or illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate.</p>
            <p>A falſe prophet or a falſe teacher may be ſo deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in a two fold reſpect.</p>
            <p>1. As he teaches or vents lies and falſe-hood, which is the moſt uſuall and common acceptation of the word.</p>
            <p>2. As he teaches without a commiſſion or calling. <note place="margin">Ier. 14. 14. Eſay 9. 15. Ezec. 13. 2. &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1. In the firſt notion he is a falſe prophet that teacheth lies, or delivers forth the <hi>viſions</hi> and deceit of his own heart, which he covers over with <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord</hi> Ezech. 13. 6. Ier. 28. 2. and ſo fathers his falſe dreames upon God, and his cheifeſt aime and care is not to ſting the people, but to feed his deluded followers with pleaſing things, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to tickle than to prick them, Saying to <hi>Ahab, go up &amp; proſper,</hi> 1 King. 22. 12. or <hi>God hath broken the yoke of Babylon,</hi> Jer. 28. 2. which was the advantage that <hi>Ahabs</hi> falſe prophets had of <hi>Micajab,</hi> and <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniah</hi> had of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> &amp; this obſervation the Scripture makes upon them, Thy prophets have not diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thine iniquity, to turn away thy captivity. <hi>Lam.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:159980:9"/> 2. 14. and they thinke to cauſe my people to forget my name. <hi>Ier.</hi> 22. 27. Whence it is that they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded and that all men ſpeake well of them <hi>Luk.</hi> 6 26. They are wiſer then to marre their owne mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets by ſharpe reproofes, as a cutpurſe is afraid to touch the quick with his knife leſt he looſe his prey.</p>
            <p>The character of falſe teachers is anſwerable, they are <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lying maſters</hi> ſpeaking perverſe things to <note place="margin">Druſ. praet. in 2 Pet. 2. 1.</note> draw Diſciples after them. <hi>Acts.</hi> 20. 30. and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lyes in hypocriſy, which they palliate over with <hi>It is written,</hi> or the name of the ſpirit, and are therefore called <hi>ſpirits of errour</hi> 1. Tim. 4. 1. as we are forbidden to <hi>beleeve every ſpirit.</hi> 1. Iohn. 4. 1. that is every doctrine though pretended to be from the ſpirit, for men are cunning to lay downe their baſtards at an honeſt doore, and to pin them upon the backe of ſcripture; being like to the falſe prophets in this miſ-fathering of their doctrines, as alſo in that other thing, which is the bayteing of their hookes with ſweet &amp; pleaſing baytes. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they allure as with a baite through <hi>the luſts of the fleſh and wantonneſſe.</hi> 2. Pet. 2. 18. And they promiſe liberty <hi>ver.</hi> 19. which are takeing things, that it is no wonder there are many that follow their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious wayes. <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>2. In the ſecond notion he is a falſe prophet who <note place="margin">Jer. 14. 14. Ezech. 13. 6.</note> runs indeed but is not ſent, I have not ſent theſe prophets <hi>yet they ran</hi> Ier. 23. 22. They can ſay <hi>I have dreamed, I have dreamed, ver.</hi> 25. but they have no miſſion, and ſuch a one is to be counted a falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <note n="b" place="margin">Molin. Vates cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Sive vera praedicet ſive falſa</hi> whether he preach true or falſe; The character of a falſe teacher is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable hereunto, hee is one that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſelfe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159980:9"/> called, or fills his owne hand, ſo that the queſtion is not what he teaches but by what warrant, as Cyprian <note place="margin">Cyprian in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtola ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonianum.</note> ſaid once to one that was inquiſitive what doctrine <hi>Novatian</hi> did teach, we need not (ſaith he) be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or curious to know <hi>quid ille doceat cum ſoris do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at,</hi> the like may be juſtly ſaid of falſe teachers. Its no asking what they teach ſince they have no cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to teach, There are found in the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, (I had almoſt ſaid in <hi>England) Falſe Chriſts, falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, falſe Prophets, falſe teachers,</hi> all theſe rankes are counterfeited, as he is called a falſe Chriſt, a falſe Apoſtle, who pretends to be Chriſt or an Apoſtle &amp; is not, ſo is he a falſe teacher who pretends to be a teacher and is not ſent. Nor is it any wonder that when once men do begin to looke for a new Chriſt, or new Apoſtles, or new Prophets, they ſhould in the next place fall to making of them, that ſo their ſeeking may not ſeeme fruſtrate, but becauſe ſome are of opinion that preaching of the word is not ſo much an act of office as of gifts, and that gifts and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents doe carry with them letters patents of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to trade with them, I muſt crave leave to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a few words upon it, becauſe it hath been ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received in the Church that both matter and forme, miſſion and viſion, gifts and calling muſt concurr to the conſtitution of him who exerciſes a publike miniſtry. For even our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in whom all fullneſſe dwells: glorified not himſelfe to be made a high Prieſt, but was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of <hi>God as was Aaron. Heb.</hi> 5. 4. 5. and the rule is there given, that no man takes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an honour or office to himſelfe, whatſoever be his parts or abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; the apoſtle ſaith not how ſhould they <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159980:10"/> 
               <hi>publikely preach</hi> the word, without gifts, and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? but, except they be ſent <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 15. It muſt not be denyed, that every member in the body hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his proper office, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 4. 5. wherby it may contribute to the good and edification of the whole. The word of God that dwells in any, ought to diffuſe it ſelfe for the benefit of others, in their families, relations, and converſations. The talent which God hath given to every one is to be put forth to uſe, the Samaritan woman may call out her neighbours to Chriſt, and the ſhepeards may ſpread abroad what they have heard of him, though they be but ſhepheards and neither prieſts nor Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, but every ſtarr in his owne orbe or Sphaere, <note n="a" place="margin">Bellarm. de eccleſia mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante.</note> 
               <hi>diverſa eſt ratio membri &amp; inſtrumenti publici</hi> there is a difference betweene a private member of the Church, and a publike inſtrument. For all the free-men of this City or corporation are not Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the edification of the body by miniſtry, and by memberſhip are plainely diſtinguiſht, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>ver</hi> 11. and 16. If every <hi>Phaeton</hi> that thinkes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe able may drive the charriot of the ſun no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the world be ſet on fire, I ſhould not doubt to ſay, that as in ſome caſes <hi>Omnis homo miles</hi> againſt a ſuddaine aſſaulter or invader, every man is a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, ſo, as the caſe may bee, <hi>omnis Chriſtianus Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſta</hi> every Chriſtian is an Evangeliſt, as <hi>Edeſius &amp; Frumentius</hi> publiſht the Goſpell to the <hi>Indies,</hi> and the woman to the <hi>Iberians,</hi> as the Eccleſiaſticall ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crates lib. 1. <hi>chap. 15. 16.</hi> Theod r. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chap 23.</hi>
               </note> reporteth, And it is ſaid <hi>Acts.</hi> 8 4. thoſe that were diſperſed by the perſecution againſt the Church at Ieruſalem, went every where preaching the word, They diſſeminated the knowledge of Chriſt, to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159980:10"/> ignorant <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Helleniſts. Acts.</hi> 11. 20. the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance defends the action, if it could be proved that theſe diſperſed Chriſtians were private men and that they preacht the word in Ieruſalem which was a conſtituted Church, before they were ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Mornay du pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the Church, <hi>ch 11.</hi>
               </note> thence, it would be ſome thing to the purpoſe, The noble <hi>Mornay</hi> puts another caſe, that if the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinells be in a dead ſleep any common ſouldier or man, may give the alarum to the City, as when the dogs do not barke the geeſe do ſave the <hi>capitol,</hi> and yet it remaines good, that there is an office, in the hands whereof Chriſt hath lodged the ſtewardſhip of the miſteries of God, the word and ſacraments, for teaching and baptizing are both put into the ſame hand; It is not a mans able parts which make him the ſteward of any of your houſes, but your committing the keyes into his hand. Nor abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, but commiſſion, which makes an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, what if a <hi>Gibeonite</hi> or any other man was able, and had the skill to dreſſe a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and performe all the outward work there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about as well as any Prieſt, Muſt hee therefore take upon him to uſurpe the Prieſts Office? I think none will ſay it, <hi>No conſtituted Church either under the Law or Goſpel can be denied to have had Officers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the worke of the Miniſtry and diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy things of God;</hi> As concerning the Church under the Law who can doubt of it? And for the Churches under the Goſpel that they ſhould be conſtituted and founded by Chriſt and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles who were <hi>ſent,</hi> (for its ſaid <hi>John</hi> 20. 21.) <hi>As my Father hath ſent me, ſo ſend I you</hi>) and then that all <hi>ſending</hi> ſhould determine and ceaſe, as if Chriſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159980:11"/> had given Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, but no Paſtors, and Teachers, can enter into no mans head, till ſenſe and reaſon be firſt gone out of it; what elſe ſhould bee the meaning of thoſe words, <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Elders, Rulers, Biſhops, Paſtors, Governours,</hi> which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinguiſht to the Community of the Church. As the Elders and whole Church Acts 15. Rulers and Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. verſe 24. Angells and Churches, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. 20. and the one ſort are ſaid to Rule and governe. The other enjoyned to ſubmit and obey them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. for ſo doubtleſſe Chriſt hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this houſe of his, as other houſes are; This City as other cities, this body or common-wealth as other ſocieties. That is, to conſiſt of ſuch as govern &amp; ſuch as are Governed: for otherwiſe it would be more like a Cyclops den then an ordered family. If any ſhall ſay that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doe ſignifie nothing but one that carries the lanthorne of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or goes before others by good example, let him ſayalſo that a Maſter or a father of a family doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 4. 5. <hi>give but a good example,</hi> to his houſe, as a very ſervant may doe, or that Joſeph was ſet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Acts.</hi> 7. 10. a good example to Egypt, and no more, The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to preach</hi> is in the new teſtament moſt uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and for the moſt part appropriated to preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by office and authority, and when the Apoſtle ſaith 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 12. I permit not a woman to teach <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nor to exerciſe authority (as the word <note place="margin">f <hi>Docere eſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poteſlatis. Calvin in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> ſignifies) it is plainely ſignified that to teach in the Church is an act of authority; thoſe then to whom the Apoſtle commended the overſight of the Church at his farewell. <hi>Acts.</hi> 20. 28. to whom <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:159980:11"/> wrote and charged them with the flocke 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 1. whom the golden Candleſticks had for their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, and upon whom that comfortable promiſe is entaild, I will be with you alwayes unto the end of the world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20. are men in office, not indeed called unto Lordſhip and dominion, but to a miniſtry and ſtewardſhip which is to be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by that moſt excellent rule and to that onely end <hi>For your edification and not for your deſtruction</hi> 2. Cor. 10. 8.</p>
            <p>But this office is undermined and pulled downe by piece-meale, ſtone by ſtone, as if a man ſhould ſay this ſtone is not eſſentiall to the houſe, nor this nor that, and ſo pull all downe at laſt. This is a ſtratagem of <hi>the Socinian</hi> art; It is ſaid that impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands in ordination is but a ceremony, or formality, and in it ſelfe a cyphar; and being ſo why may it not be laid aſide as well as that ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of laying the Bible on the head, which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the <note n="a" place="margin">Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagin 4. c. 2.</note> counſell of Carthage? concerning impoſition of hands in the generall this I ſay that it is not a thing to be ſlighted as an outward rite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous to the ſpiritualneſſe of the Goſpell for its one of thoſe which the Apoſtle calls the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt and the foundation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1. 2. and for the particular place it hath in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, let it firſt be ſettled &amp; agreed that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry being an office or calling hath ſome way of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into it appointed by him that hath appointed the office, &amp; that there is a ſeparation of men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, or manner of their conſtitution &amp; ordination, that is, a poteſtative miſſion as ſome expreſſe it: and then the <hi>modus</hi> is to be inquired into as touching
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159980:12"/> which, it is argued that ordination by impoſition of hands as contradiſtinguiſht from the election of the people is not eſſential to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of entrance. <hi>Eſ-ſentiall</hi> is a great word. Baptiſme &amp; the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per are not eſſentiall to the being of a Chriſtian or to ſalvation; ſo as the privation of them ſhould damne the ſoule, and yet are of excellent uſe and cleare inſtitution. It may ſuffice, that there is ſo much in the word for ordination as that the way of the word in that caſe is neither to be laid aſide nor receded from, nor maimed. The engine planted for battery and overthrow of ordination is the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people that is the <hi>id ipſum</hi> wherein the ſeparation of a man to the miniſtry doth conſiſt, and yet we read of a ſeparation unto God for the worke of the miniſtry by faſting, prayer, and impoſition of hands, without any election of people, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 1. 2. I am of <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. de rep eccl. 2. <hi>cap. 2.</hi> para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Spalato</hi> his minde that this was not a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to an office which Paul and Barnabas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had not, but that it was a ſeparation unto God (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) for the worke of the Miniſtry, is cleere enough, and what was that worke, but the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word and ordaining of elders. <hi>Acts.</hi> 14. 23. 24. 25. 26. If any man can ſhew throughout the New-Teſtament that any did impoſe hands for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of men to the office or worke of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry but onely ſuch as were in office themſelves, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Evangeliſts, Elderſhip,</hi> and theſe <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> or that the election of the people is the <hi>id ipſum</hi> of ſeparation, let it be done, or let us have leſſe dictating and leſſe begging, for by the way let me tell you, wee live in the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garlieſt age that ever was, I meane for <hi>begging of the queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:159980:12"/>
            <p>And if the meere election of the people be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, what neede was there that the Apoſtle ſhould leave <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> for this cauſe, that hee might ordaine Elders in every City, <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 5. For if it be ſaid that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that thou mighteſt ordain, be no more then that thou mighteſt ordain, be no more then that thou mighteſt looke on while the people did it, Then why may not <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (of whom it is ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee conſtituted <hi>Joſeph</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over Aegypt) bee ſaid to looke on only, while the people did it. And what need was there that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſhould be ſeparated and ſent forth to ordaine Elders in every Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. If the Churches election had beene the <hi>id ipſum</hi> of ordination; And why are the characters and qualifications of Elders and Biſhops given and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. Not ſo much to the people, by which they ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in their elections, as to them who were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ordaine them, that they might not lay on hands ſuddenly, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. In which place laying on of hands (as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews) is put for ordination, and ſo is not election by the people any where found to be. As for Caſes and inſtances of a people caſt up in ſome remote Iſland or the like: may not they chuſe a Miniſter? and he perform the office without ordination? ſuch caſes may bee formed to overthrow any common rule or law of Miniſtery or Magiſtracy either. It's ſaid that an <note n="a" place="margin">Exceptio fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat regulam in non exceptis.</note> exception ſtrengthens a rule, &amp; over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws it not, for then there could be no rule of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, becauſe every rule hath ſome exception; ſet the Heteroclites by themſelves, and let the rule ſtand. If <hi>David</hi> eate the Shew-bread, or the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159980:13"/> performe that office which belongs to the Prieſts (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 34. with <hi>Levit.</hi> 1. 6.) in caſe of neceſſity; there is no more can be ſaid but <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas quod cogit, defendit,</hi> that which neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, it defends.</p>
            <p>That the holy Ghoſt was given by the impoſition of the Apoſtles hands; (I ſay the <hi>Apoſtles</hi>) Act. 8. 18. is true: but no argument againſt laying on of hands by the Elderſhip in ordination, for there were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers reaſons and occaſions of laying on of hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in ordination: <hi>and other hands</hi> were laid on in ordination, than could give the holy Ghoſt. The Levites had impoſition of hands (<note n="a" place="margin">Fagius in Chald. paraph. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>tanquam in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium,</hi> Numb. 8. 10, 11. as upon a ſacrifice) dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating them to God and his ſervice. And ſo in the New Teſtament, it was uſed for ſeparation of men to the worke or office of the Miniſtery: but there is no miracle wrought, nor is the holy Ghoſt given, nor any inward grace. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>grace</hi> ſeems <hi>ſomewhere</hi> to be put for <hi>office,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 5. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Rom. 1. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; 15. 15, 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gal. 2. 9.</hi> Groti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Beza, Dieu. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Grace and Apoſtleſhip,</hi> that is, the grace of Apoſtleſhip, &amp; in this ſenſe (as <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith) if that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or grace be taken, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. Then may it be ſaid to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with impoſition of the hands of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. As for election by the people, which is by ſome cryed up as the <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All</hi> in this point, though I have nothing to ſay againſt the lawfullneſſe of it, where it's duely conditioned: yet if any ſhall plead the neceſſity of it as eſſentiall to the calling of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, I ſhould not ſtick to ſay, <hi>that there is clearer evidence in Scripture for ordination of Miniſters by impoſition of hands, then for election by the people.</hi> That word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. out of which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159980:13"/> it is expiſcate, after a man hath made the beſt of it, will leave him to beg the queſtion, for there appeares in it no act of the Church at all: but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſignifies, it refers wholly to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> who did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ordaine Elders for the Diſciples, and therefore without endangering not only the ſenſe, but the grammer of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can no more referre to the people, then <note n="c" place="margin">Diatrib p. 6. &amp; page 10.</note> he that affirmes that it may, can prove <hi>Luke</hi> to bee an Apoſtle (as he ſtiles him.) I deny not that <hi>Cheiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonia</hi> in the <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Zonar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Can.</hi> 1.</note> original and firſt riſe of the word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a giving vote or ſuffrage by ſtretching forth the hand, or an election manifeſted by that ſigne, but the <hi>uſe</hi> of words, not the <hi>Etymology</hi> muſt rule their interpretation; and it is paſt all queſtion that the Greeke Heathen Authours doe uſe this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>generally,</hi> to <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Heſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch.</hi>
               </note> conſtitute, appoint, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, as is obſerved by <hi>Heſychius,</hi> as they doe alſo <note n="f" place="margin">So alſo in Scripture, <hi>Acts 1. 26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to reckon or give ſentence, though there be no uſe of <hi>counters</hi> or <hi>little ſtones:</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to bee choſen to a place, or to obtaine a poſſeſſion, though there be no uſe of any <hi>Lot</hi> therein, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> a man may bee ſaid <hi>pedibus ire in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam,</hi> though he have no feet to goe upon: but becauſe we would not reſt in generals, let us examin what was the act of <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas</hi> in this place: for it is plaine that they put <note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 11.</note> forth ſome particular act, when 'its ſaid <hi>they ordained for them</hi> or unto them <hi>Elders,</hi> did they <hi>ordaine by impoſition</hi> of hands? as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies in the Greeke Fathers and counſells who may be thought to underſtand the language) It is not unlikely that thoſe very men that had been ſent forth upon this expedition
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159980:14"/> by impoſition of hands, faſting &amp; prayer ſhould in the like manner ordaine Elders, for ſo the very te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in hand couples together, ordaining of Elders in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Church &amp; praying with faſtings; or did they <hi>elect Elders for them?</hi> as <note n="h" place="margin">Grotius in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> Grotius ſeemes to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it, but thoſe that contend for that ſenſe of the <hi>word,</hi> to ſignify <hi>election,</hi> will not eaſily diſgeſt the <hi>interpretation,</hi> and the truth is, They that argue the peoples election of Miniſters, from the election of the ſeven, <hi>Acts.</hi> 6. which the Apoſtles permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the people there, cannot eaſily grant that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did aſſume it to themſelves here, becauſe it gives away the queſtion, namely election by the people; or did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas joyne with the Diſciples in election?</hi> If it had been ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it had been ſomething to the purpoſe, but it is not ſaid they <hi>choſe with them,</hi> but they <hi>ordained for them Elders</hi> in every Church, And for that which <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Credibile eſt &amp;c.</hi> I'ts to be thought that the conſent of the people went along alſo, the reaſon that he gives, namely becauſe in a leſſer matter their conſent was ſometime taken in, quite overthrowes that which is contended for <hi>ex vt verbi</hi> out of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, uſed in the text, and we know that where the Apoſtles, Elders, and Brethren concurred in an act they are all named <hi>Acts.</hi> 15. 23. which as here it is not ſaid ſo it cannot hence be proved; or in the laſt place, if it be ſaid that the word tranſlated, <hi>ordaine,</hi> ſignifies <hi>an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon a previous or antecedent election of the people,</hi> then 'its cleare that <hi>election</hi> doth not thruſt out <hi>ordination</hi> nor the act of the people juſtle out the act of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and ſo that engine
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159980:14"/> workes not by this Text, which is ſo much clearer for ordination than election, as the act of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> is more expreſſe then that couchant act of the people, which is pretended to lie hid in the ſame word: which if it be taken in one ſimple ſenſe, <hi>ſignifying either</hi> generally to conſtitute or ordaine, and ſo relate to the act of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thruſting into the notion of the word either impoſition of hands (which may be made good elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in Scripture to have beene uſed in ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or election by the people, which cannot be made good elſewhere) <hi>or ſignifying</hi> election by ſuffrage, and ſo relate both to <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas</hi> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as if they all concur'd in election or vote, and that was all they did: both theſe ſignifications the word will beare, though not the Text: but if it carry twins in the belly of it, and import two divers acts different in kinde, and ſo relate to ſome act of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> differing from the act or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of the people, then muſt that ſignification be proved by good examples, leſt it bee found ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have beene ſo uſed before <hi>Luke</hi> uſed it ſo: but I hold my hand from further proſecution of this Scripture, and offer to you one obſervation more, tending to cleare the point in hand, and that is out of <hi>Acts</hi> 6. where it is cleare that there was an electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>ſeven,</hi> and as cleare, that the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ordination of them was reſerved unto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>verſ. 6. Looke yee out ſeven men whom wee may appoint</hi> or conſtitute <hi>over this buſineſs;</hi> the people elected, the Apoſtles ordained, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. &amp; 5. But the election is not called the conſtitution or ordination, for that the Apoſtles are ſaid to doe:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159980:15"/> and how did they doe it? <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. when they had prayed <hi>they laid their hands on them,</hi> ordination by impoſition of hands was the conſtitutive act. The peoples <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ver. 6. and the Apoſtle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 3. are not all one: that poore criticiſme would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have beene borne, if the <note n="f" place="margin">Diatrib p 10.</note> Author of it had but ſet the words together <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the people <hi>ſet</hi> or preſented the elected before the Apoſtles, they did not ordaine them before the Apoſtles, but preſented them to be conſtituted and ordained by them <hi>over that buſineſs</hi> unto which they were choſen, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. There is not a more uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all word in the <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. politic. paſſim.</hi> Acts 7. 10. 27. 35. Mat. 24. 47. &amp; 25. 41. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. 12. 14. Acts 6. 3. Titus 1. 5. uſually with the prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the place or the ſubject matter of their office &amp; gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
               <hi>greeke tongue,</hi> to ſignifie the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a Governour, or ſetling one into an office or praefecture then this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is alſo uſed for the conſtitution of Elders and Church Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in the new Teſtament, which wee call <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you pleaſe to conſult the practiſe of antiquity in the point of election of Biſhops <hi>ab ordine &amp; plebe</hi> (as they uſe to ſay) by the Church officers and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, you ſhall finde 1. That election was never ſet ſo high as to give checke to ordination, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted that wherein the miſſion or ſending did conſiſt: but as a preparative to ordination by way of good teſtimony of the perſon to bee ordained. 2. When you have ſearcht all records (as <note n="b" place="margin">Spalato derep. eccleſ. lib. 3. cap. 3.</note> they are laid together by a very learned hand) the reſult and ſumme will be this, that <hi>election</hi> had the force on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a nomination, preſentation, poſtulation, or conſent, ſo as a Miniſter could not bee obtruded <hi>invitae eccleſiae</hi> upon a Church whether it would or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if they were able to put in a juſt exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159980:15"/> him, for which end the perſon to be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned was firſt to be proclaimed, or (as I may ſay) <hi>asked in</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Concil. Chalced. can. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Church,</hi> for the very reaſon of <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cyprian Ep. 68. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> ſpeech, that the people principally have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to <hi>chuſe the worthy,</hi> or <hi>refuſe the unworthy,</hi> is rendred in the ſame <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> that they do fully know the <hi>life &amp; converſation</hi> of every man. And therefore it is <note n="e" place="margin">Diatrib. <hi>cap. 11.</hi>
               </note> injudiciouſly ſpoken that <hi>ordination</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows election: for an irrational or meer arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary diſſent, when no juſt exception could be put in bar againſt a man, could no more hinder a mans or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, then ſuch a peeviſhneſſe now a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> days can hinder the marriage of one whoſe name is publiſht in the congregation. <hi>Ab ordinatoribus plebs docen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da non ſequenda,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caeleſtinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cloze of this point might well have beene an <hi>Apology</hi> for ſpeaking ſo much of it in this place, had not the Text led me to ſay ſomething, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the times, together with the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion conſtrained me to this prolixity. For the <hi>office</hi> of the Miniſtery, and the power thereunto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, are very much undervalued, and laid very low by many: who differing among themſelves in principles, doe as in a common intereſt, joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to cry downe and degrade them, In order to a <hi>two-fold liberty.</hi> The one is the <hi>liberty of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying</hi> or preaching, as any man is able to ſet up the trade: in oppoſition to which they conceive the Miniſters do ſtand for their own livings and power ſake. The other is the <hi>liberty of their luſts</hi> and ways of looſeneſſe, and theſe are ſuch upon whom the feare of the Miniſtery is fallen, whoſe Spirit cannot bear too free reproofe, nor their courſes a too cloſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159980:16"/> obſervation. And hence it is that ſome of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving learning, doe ſet their wits on worke to rout this office and the power thereof, by bafling the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of the word, and endeavouring to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Scripture out of doores, which though God hath not pleaſed to deliver <hi>Syſtematically</hi> in a way of abſolute precept or demonſtrative clearneſſe in every particular, yet ought to be regarded in the hints and conſequences and implications which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford foot-hold to a good conſcience, and not to be out-wrangled for our ends and luſts ſake, as being the becke of that great God who is able to becken us all into nothing, others that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate by the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> of policy, doe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover or imagine future inconveniences, which may ariſe from the indiſcretion, paſſion, weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Miniſters, and if they will but goe on to play that Cannon a little further, they ſhall find it will batter and overthrow all Magiſtracy, or any government that is managed by men; others whoſe tongues are ſharper then their arguments fall foule upon the miniſtry, and poure treble contempt upon it, in lieu of double honour, never was mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry more bleſſed and witneſſed unto from heaven, by the ſucceſſe and fruitfullneſſe of it in bringing in and bringing up, a people unto God, (though ſome of their chickens are caught and carried away by kites or have forſaken them, as duckes forſake the hen that hatched them) never more contemned That which the<hi rend="sup">f</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collat. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Donatiſt</hi> objected ſometime to <hi>Auſtin</hi> is now rife againe <hi>tu quis es? Filius es Ceci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liani, an non?</hi> who ordained you, you are the brat of <hi>Cecilian,</hi> are you not? (whom they pretended
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159980:16"/> to be a <hi>traditor</hi> or to have given up the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the fire) ſo they ſay to the Miniſters, whoſe ſons are you? is not your pedigree by lineall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent from <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> is not he the top of your kin? he that hath but halfe an eye may ſee the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the Wolves would have the Sheep to quitt their dogs. The miniſtry if encouraged and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to doe their duty, will be (next under the Parliament, who, we hope, will doe theirs) the greateſt bulwarke or banke againſt the inundation of errour, haereſy, and blaſphemy, whoſe increaſe is the occaſion of this humiliation; It is the lot of the Miniſters of the reformed Churches to be grund betweene two Mil-ſtones, in the firſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the popiſh Champions fell pell-mell upon the calling of the <note n="a" place="margin">Non miſſi non vocati non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrati. Briſtow motiu.</note> Miniſters of the reformed Churches pretending it to be null (<hi>ac proinde nulla eccleſia,</hi> and conſequently (ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Non ab epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis ordinati ac proinde nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la eccleſia Greg de Valentia. <hi>Tom. 4. diſput.</hi> 9. queſt. 3. <hi>punct 2. in fine.</hi>
               </note> Gregory <hi>de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi>) (the Churches no Churches) becauſe they were <hi>not ordained by Biſhops.</hi> The ſame concluſion is now undertaken; <hi>That the preſent Miniſters in this Church are not lawfull Miniſters,</hi> upon a <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> quite contrary, that is, becauſe <hi>they were ordained by Biſhops,</hi> nor are thoſe who are ordained by <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> in much better account with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectours, for they are in the ſame line of pedigree, being but once more removed from the ſtocke, great-grandchildren, to the Pope; The cauills of the Papiſts have been long agoe laid to ſleepe by the anſwers of <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mornay of the Church. chap. 11.</hi> Sadeel de legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim, vocat. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. reform. eccle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſt. Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cano.</note> learned men, who have diſtinguiſht be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the corruptions in the perſons ordaining or in the <hi>fieri</hi> of ordination, and the ſubſtance and validity of ordination <hi>in facto eſſe,</hi> and the very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:159980:17"/> ſame anſwers which were made for the firſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and the Miniſters ordained by them, are of as full force for the Miniſters now in being with us, and the Miniſters ordained by them, nor can our Miniſtery fall by this argument now uſed againſt us, without the fall of all miniſtery in the Churches of Chriſt in all times and places where Biſhops had a hand in ordination, and if the Scripture doe ſettle the power of ordination in <hi>a Preſbytery</hi> or in the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church, it can never be made good, that a <hi>Biſhops</hi> hand (who is alſo a <hi>preſbyter</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned with others, can anull the ordination, as neither is Baptiſme a nullity becauſe admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by a Biſhop and haply with ſome corrupt ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony uſed in the adminiſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the <hi>ſecond point</hi> which I will touch but breifly and reſerve the uſe of both and of that which followes untill the cloſe of all.</p>
            <p>Theſe falſe teachers are they that bring in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Hereſies, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Stuprant veritatem adulterio haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tertull. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> They defloure the truth by haereticall adultery not onely thoſe that teach without <hi>commiſſion,</hi> but ſuch as have a calling to teach doe by doctrines of errour bring in damnable haereſies, as its ſaid Acts. 20. 30. <hi>Alſo of your own ſelves,</hi> ſhall men ariſe ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing perverſe things to draw Diſciples after them-They called <hi>Paul</hi> (becauſe he was a zealous teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Goſpell) <hi>a ringleader of the ſect of the Nazarens, Acts.</hi> 24. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies one that is the firſt man of the ranke, it is a <hi>military</hi> word, and I wiſh that our <hi>military</hi> men had not transfuſed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour into the ſeverall parts of our body. If it be ſaid that many of thoſe who are charged with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159980:17"/> teaching of errours or haereſy are holy men, I anſwer that a holy man cannot eaſily be a haeretick, nor are all the errous of holy men to be called haereſy though they may be Hay and Stubble upon the foundation, but it hath been obſerved of old that ſome <hi>haereſiarchs</hi> or heads of haereſy have been well reputed for ſtrictneſſe and unblameableneſſe of life: we learn out of <hi>Auſtine,</hi> that <note n="a" place="margin">Pelagij nomen non ſine laude aliqua poſui quia vita ejus a multis praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur. <hi>Retract. lib. 2. cap. 33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pelagius</hi> had a very good teſtimony, and Scripture tells us they come <hi>in Sheeps cloathing</hi> and ſpeake lies in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy. Lies would not take, if they were not co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ended by the holineſſe of the perſon, and guilded over as a rotten nutmegge with gold, There is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>or tranſformation</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> into an Angell <hi>of light,</hi> of <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> into the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of Satans <hi>Miniſters</hi> into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13. 14. 14. and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not meaſure or judge of <note n="b" place="margin">Ex perſonis fidem? an ex ſide perſonas? Tertull. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcip.</note> faith by the perſon but of the perſon by the faith. Truth may be as a Iewell in a dunghill, and errour carried (as <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi> carried his poyſon) in a Gold-ring, That <hi>horſe</hi> of ſuperſtition and idolatry, upon the back of which the Divell hath in former times made warr againſt the Church is ſlain under him, and now he is mounted upon a freſh horſe of another colour, called <hi>liberty of opinion,</hi> falſely called liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>Lets not be ignorant of his devices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I paſſe on to the ſecond part of the text. <hi>The ſeed which theſe falſe teachers doe ſow,</hi> and the text ſaith <hi>They ſhall privily bring in damnable haereſies even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought them,</hi> in which wordes we take up theſe three things.</p>
            <p>1. That haereſies are damnable.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:159980:18"/>
            <p>2. That damnable haereſies are brought in privily.</p>
            <p>3. That thoſe which bring them in doe evende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Lord that bought them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt open theſe in few words, and then come to the inveſtigation or ſearching out what hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie is, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is here by the Apoſtle called damnable.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt you ſee that haereſies are ſaid to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable or deſtructive. <hi>Haereſies of deſtruction</hi> as its ſaid, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 5. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a man of bloods, that is a bloody man: but why ſhould haereſies be emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally called <hi>haereſies of deſtruction?</hi> for is not all ſin of damnable guilt? and is not death the wages <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſin as ſin? Its true; And yet as <hi>Judas</hi> that was an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, and an eminent Diſciple of Chriſt, and betrayed and ſold him for money, is called, <hi>John</hi> 17. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſon of deſtruction, and as the Antichriſt is alſo called, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 3. the man of ſinne, the ſonne of deſtruction, becauſe under Chriſts name and colours he fights againſt him, and ſerves his own luſts upon the profeſſion of his name, and ſo ſhall fall under more eminent and remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable deſtruction. So Haeretickes who profeſſing Chriſtianity, and the name of Chriſt, doe denye him, or adulterate his trueth for their owne ends and luſts, ſhall come under more heavy and ſore damnation, which is aggravated by that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Swift deſtruction,</hi> which ſhall fall upon their heads violently and unexpectedly: <hi>for their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lingreth not, and their damnation ſlumbreth not,</hi> verſ. 3. And that it may appeare that God had an eye of wrath and vengeance upon this kinde of men long agoe. Its ſaid by our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. their judgment <hi>now of a long time</hi> lingreth not: and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159980:18"/> by <hi>Jude,</hi> verſ. 4. that <hi>they were of olde ordained to this condemnation</hi> or judgement, which new and unuſuall expreſſions or aggravations of the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this kinde of men, doe give ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>haereſies</hi> are called <hi>haereſies of deſtruction:</hi> whether the word <hi>damnable</hi> be <hi>reſtrictive</hi> to ſome haereſies, as implying that there are ſome that are not damnable; or whether it be <hi>deſcriptive,</hi> as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing what haereſies are <note n="c" place="margin">Gerard in locum.</note> (<hi>in ſuo genere</hi>) in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, muſt be anſwered and reſolved by the definition or deſcription of haereſie, <hi>what it is:</hi> and if we either looke at that deſcription of it, which is implied in this Text, to bee <hi>a denying of the Lord the Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> or which is given of it in any place, in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall Epiſtles;</hi> we ſhall find, that in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture acceptation &amp; deſcription of haereſie, All haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is damnable, not that every Haeretick is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and peremptorily damned: for then I ſee no more reaſon for admoniſhing an haeretick, then for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for one that hath ſinned a ſin unto death; even <hi>Judas</hi> called the ſon of perdition, had hee had (as ſome of the Ancients ſay) <hi>Peters</hi> repentance, might have found forgiveneſſe as he did: but there is this marke ſet upon haereſie, that we may all heare and feare and doe no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>2. Damnable haereſies are brought in privily, words of this decompoſition as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doe ſignifie <hi>inſinuation,</hi> theſe tares are ſowne while men ſleep, in a clancular or ſubtill way whereof men are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, as its ſaid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 4. Falſe brethren <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Gal. 2. 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>at una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, privily</hi> crept in, and <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jude 4.</hi>
               </note> Certain men are <hi>crept in privily,</hi> meaning Haereſy-maſters or falſe teachers. <hi>Haereſie</hi> is modeſt at firſt, and inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:159980:19"/> as the Serpent into <hi>Eve</hi> by ſubtle fetches and <hi>quaeres, yea, hath God ſaid?</hi> Gen. 3. 1. or by ſweete promiſes and inducements, <hi>ye ſhall not ſurely dye, ye ſhall be as Gods, your eyes ſhall be opened,</hi> verſ. 4. 5. So its ſaid, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. they ſhall make merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of you. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with fine forms of ſpeech, words compoſed for the nonce. The Apoſtle ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that there is a ſubtilty, or as you might ſay a myſtery in this Trade of corrupting mens mindes from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 14. And ſometimes they worke by the wife (as the Serpent did) to give her husband the apple: they draw men as Juglers doe a pieoe of mony with a fine inviſible haire, and never bring forth the <hi>portenta</hi> of their opinions, until their <hi>ſigmenta</hi> have made the way: they mixe their droſſe among good ſilver, and lap up errour in the pap of truth, that ſome parts of the monſter may have their true ſhape.</p>
            <p>3. Theſe that bring in theſe damnable haereſies doe even deny the Lord that bought them, and here I might take in hand two ſorts of opinions. The firſt is that of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who deny that Chriſt by a proper ſatisfaction made to the juſtice of God, did buy or purchaſeus. To theſe the ſinger of the Text ſeemes directly to point: for they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny the Lord Chriſts theanthropie? but his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by way of purchaſe. The other is that of <note n="f" place="margin">Lutherani, alijque.</note> ſome that hence inferre an univerſall redemption, becauſe that theſe that bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction are ſaid to bee <hi>bought by</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">f</hi> 
               <hi>Chriſt:</hi> of both which points I cannot ſay a little without ſpeaking much, and therefore ſhall hold me to my ſubject in hand; wee may partly perceive by this expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159980:19"/> what damnable haereſies are: for its ſaid that they who bring them in, doe even deny the Lord that bought them; If they deny Chriſt the Soveraigne Lord <note n="o" place="margin">See Jude, v. 4.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) by everting his perſon or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. If they deny his redemption and ſo evert his office (whether his Lordſhip or his redemption bee denyed) the haereſie is damnable, and the word <hi>denying</hi> ſeems to me to imply, that the proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of haereſie is to bee <note n="g" place="margin">Spalato, oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſio errorum Suareſij <hi>cap. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>euerſive</hi> and overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: It conſiſts not properly in additions to the word, ſaving ſo farre as thoſe additions are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the pillars and foundations of truth; that is, Chriſt the Lord that bought us, or the like to it: for if hay and ſtubble be built on this foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 12. becauſe they doe not overthrow it, or ſhake and ſhiver it, therefore though they be errours yet they are not haereſie. <hi>Non omnis error eſt haereſis</hi> (ſaith <note n="h" place="margin">Ad quod vult deum in praefat. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi>) every Errour is not hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſic: and therefore <hi rend="sup">i</hi> ſome diſtinguiſh of doctrines <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Weems.</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the 4 de generate ſons. <hi>pag.</hi> 180.</note> or errours thus: ſome are <hi>praeter,</hi> ſome are <hi>circa,</hi> ſome are <hi>contra fundamentum,</hi> that is (as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith) ſome <hi>touch not,</hi> ſome <hi>ſhake,</hi> and ſome raze the foundation. The weight and valour of doctrines muſt be reckoned by their proximity or neareneſſe to the fundamentals: for it is in the <hi>Conſanguinity of doctrine</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls it) as it is <hi>in kindred,</hi> the neereneſſe of kindred is to be meaſured by neerneſſe to the ſtocke.</p>
            <p>This denyall of the Lord that bought them, may be either expreſly <hi>conceptis verbis</hi> and ſo with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more height of expreſſion may amount to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, but haply theſe in the text who uſed <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed wordes</hi> were not ſo blacke mouth'd, or this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:159980:20"/> may be <hi>interpretativè</hi> and by conſequence: and the conſequence is either from their doctrines or a conſequence of fact alſo, from their courſe or converſation.</p>
            <p>The conſequence from their doctrines (if it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the faith) muſt not be drawn out into a long chaine and farr fetcht, leaſt by that meanes every errour be made haereſy, but the conſequence muſt be neere and cloſe, ſo that you may be able to ſay this or that doctrine or opinion at the next remove or at a very neer diſtance denyes the onely ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Jude 4. the battery may ſtrike off a tile or make a hole in the wall, but except it be neere, will not overthrow the foundation, for as from every branch of a great tree one may goe or move to the root, yet the cutting off of any twigge or branch is not a cutting down or rooting up the tree, ſo though all branches of truth have continuity with the fundamentalls or principles, yet the deniall of every truth is not a razing or overthrow of them, I inſtance in the great principle, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus is the Lord that hath bought us,</hi> not becauſe there are not other which being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, faith is overthrown, but becauſe it is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in my text, and in Jude. 4. and alſo becauſe principles lie ſo cloſe together, and are ſo concente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate that an errour which routs one, routes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by immediate conſequence. I will give one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or two, Suppoſe the reſurrection future bee denyed, this overthrowes the faith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 18. and ſee how the conſequence immediately ſhatters all principles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 13. If there be no reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead, <hi>Then</hi> is Chriſt not riſen, <hi>Then</hi> is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:159980:20"/> our preaching vaine, <hi>Then</hi> is faith vaine, <hi>Then</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are yet in their ſins. <hi>Then</hi> the dead in Chriſt are periſht, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Or ſuppoſe the Law bee brought into equipage with Chriſt for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, marke the conſequence. If ſo (ſaith the Apoſtle) then <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing,</hi> Gal. 5. 2. <hi>Chriſt is become of none effect unto you,</hi> verſe 4. <hi>Yee are fallen from grace,</hi> and I make no doubt to ſay that thoſe of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> who for their carnall ends, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 12, 13. did breake the continuity and communion of the Church, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves up to this opinion, <hi>were haereticks,</hi> not while it was an opinion in debate or controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: but when it grew into a ripe Impoſtume in ſuch as adhaered to it: and do but obſerve in both the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances given, by how immediate conſequence the denyall of the reſurrection, or the contempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Law with Chriſt, doe overthrow the fundamentall of Fundamentalls, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in reſpect of his redemption or office.</p>
            <p>For that which I call conſequence of fact, from the courſe or converſation of Haeretickes: I obſerve that both the Apoſtle in this Chapter, and <hi>Jude</hi> in his Epiſtle, who follows the ſame thred in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of them, do characteriſe them by the Iuſts and fleſhy courſes wherein they live. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of falſe teachers, as is evident by that he exhorts Chriſtians <hi>to contend for the faith:</hi> becauſe certain men were crept in privily or unawares, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. 4 He exemplifies the deſtruction of theſe by the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> examples of the <hi>Angells that fell,</hi> and of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi> He drawes out their picture in the like foul colours: and in the fourth verſe calls <hi>them
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159980:21"/> ungodly men, turning the grace of God into laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and denying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And though luſts of the fleſh, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery and the like, cannot be called haereſie; <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> de E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl. lib. 4. part 2. cap. 1. Morton <hi>in 1 Cor. 11. 18.</hi>
               </note> yet if a man profeſſing Chriſt ſhall chuſe ſuch an <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>doctrine</hi> as doth patronize and maintain thoſe luſts, and ſo walkes in a courſe of ſinne under the protection of ſuch an opinion or tenet, as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary both to faith and holineſſe, that comes up to the Scripture-deſcription of haereſie: for ſo theſe falſe teachers that bring in damnable haereſies, are ſaid <hi>to allure through luſts of the fleſh and much wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toneſſe,</hi> ver. 18. and to promiſe <hi>liberty,</hi> as likewiſe thoſe that are entangled in their errours doe <hi>turne from</hi> the holy Commandement, and turn to their former vomit and wallowing in the mire, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. 21, 22. and ſo the <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> and the <hi>putting away</hi> of good <hi>conſcience,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 19. goe both together; and therefore the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> whoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was hatefull to Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 15. and whoſe luſts and filthineſſe maintained by their pernicious doctrine <note n="a" place="margin">Iren. <hi>lib. 1. cap. 20.</hi> Clem. Alex. <hi>lib. 7.</hi> Strom.</note> were monſtrous, can bee accounted no other then damnable Haereticks (and we may judg the like of others of the ſame ſtamp) being the very perſons (as is <note n="b" place="margin">Epiphan. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. 26. Beza <hi>in Revel. 2. 15.</hi> Quiros in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> conceived by good Authors) whom both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> deſcribe as turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe, and denying the onely Lord God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Iude</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>So much for the opening of the three points, which you may if you pleaſe bind up together <hi>into one, That falſe teachers ſhall privily bring in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable haereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:159980:21"/>
            <p>Now we come to ſearch out what <hi>Haereſie</hi> is.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>haereſie</hi> is of Greeke <hi>originall,</hi> and is often tranſlated <hi>Sect,</hi> not <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtinian</hi> in 21 et. 2.</note> 
               <hi>a ſecando</hi> from cutting, but <hi>a ſectando</hi> from following, as being a way which men chuſe to follow as its ſaid. <hi>The way</hi> which they call haereſie, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 14 <hi>A way</hi> of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or doctrine, for ſo he ſaith, ſo doe <hi>I worſhip</hi> the God of my Fathers, <hi>beleeving, &amp;c.</hi> It appeares to be an act of the will electively pitching upon ſuch a way. For the word it ſelfe ſignifies <hi>election,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming not from <note n="b" place="margin">Martinius lexicon.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to expugne or lay waſte, (though that be proper enough) but from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to chuſe or adhere unto: and therefore the <hi>Septuagint</hi> Levit. 22. 18. 21. tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>free-will offering</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> election or <hi>free-willedneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Rabbins</hi> call an Haeretick <note n="c" place="margin">Druſius de 3. ſectis Judae, <hi>lib. 1 cap. 2.</hi> Grotius <hi>in Tit. 3. 10.</hi> Nic. Fuller <hi>Miſcellan.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which in <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 1. 12. Levit. 11. 22.</note> Scripture ſignifies a kinde or <hi>ſpecies,</hi> and ſo they denote a man to be an Haereticke, who leaving the common road or way of faith and Doctrine, ſets up and followes a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> way of his own, <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Elias</hi> in <hi>Tiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> one that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> without law, that will not bee bound up by the rule, but runnes out into his owne way, and <note n="g" place="margin">Nic. Fuller <hi>miſcel.</hi> ſacra. <hi>lib. 2. cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> ſome derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. 17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 16. ſignifying to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe</hi> or <hi>deny,</hi> as if you would ſay <hi>a renegado</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyer of the trueth.</p>
            <p>This word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> while it kept it ſelfe among <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, Phyſitians,</hi> and other <hi>Profeſſors of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and learning</hi> paſt, for an <hi>honeſt word,</hi> but when it came into the Churches quarters, and was taken up by Chriſtians, it became branded, ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized and odious. Its uſed about ſixe times in the <note n="h" place="margin">Acts 5. 17. 26. 5. 15. 5. 28. 22 24. 14. 24. 5.</note> Acts of the Apoſtles, and whether it may not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159980:22"/> in ſome of thoſe places at leaſt, bee taken in good part or indifferently, ſhall not bee my diſpute at this time. But when you finde it in the Epiſtles A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall, and in the Goſpell Churches, it hath not a jot of good ſavour in it, but carries a marke of iniquity and infamy upon it: In thoſe Epiſtles it is uſed about <note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 18. Gal. 5. 20. Titus 3. 10. 2 Pet. 2. 1.</note> foure times expreſly, and becauſe I would not make a definition which you might ſay is mine owne, and ſo ſlight it, I will lay before you the Scriptures that ſpeake of it, that you may in their light ſee what it is.</p>
            <p>The firſt place is that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 18, 19. <hi>I hear that there bee Schiſmes among you, and I partly beleeve it. For there muſt bee alſo haereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Greeke Interpreters take <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> in this place, for both one in a manner, and underſtand not by the word <hi>Haereſie</hi> any matter <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Oecumen in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dogmaticall</hi> or of Doctrine: but others <note n="l" place="margin">Beza in loc.</note> argue from the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>alſo.</hi> (There muſt <hi>alſo</hi> be hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies) that they are diſtinct, and that though <hi>haereſie</hi> include <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> yet ſchiſme doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude haereſie: and to mee it ſeemes that they are neare a kinne, becauſe the Apoſtle riſes from one to the other, ſaying, there are ſchiſmes, there muſt <hi>alſo</hi> be haereſies: but they are not collaterally a kin; for by the aſcent, haereſie ſeems to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: For there muſt bee <hi>alſo</hi> haereſies, into which thoſe that are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do not <note n="m" place="margin">Neque enim eos probatos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligi jubet qui in haereſin fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem demutant Tertull. de pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> 
               <hi>eaſily fall,</hi> but are made the more conſpicuous or manifeſt for ſoundneſſe and integrity.</p>
            <p>That we may find the true nature of haereſie, let me in few words declare what ſchiſme is.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:159980:22"/>
            <p>The word <hi>ſchiſme</hi> imports a rent or diviſion of things that were or ſhould be in continuity and undevidedneſſe, and as its taken in the matter of Religion, it ſignifies a rupture in the communion, or from the communion of the Church upon unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and unwarrantable cauſes and grounds. <hi>A cauſeleſſe breaking, or breaking off from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church in matter of worſhip or Religion.</hi> Society and communion are of great importance: the evill of ſchiſme is anſwerable to the good of ſociety and communion; we are to judge of ſchiſme by the cauſe of it: For if it bee upon a cauſe which the Word warrants not, it is a ſinne of high na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <note place="margin">Cameron de Schiſmat.</note> Some diſtribute it into two ſorts or parts, <hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
               <hi>negative</hi> and <hi>poſitive. Negative</hi> is the very rupture and breaking off: <hi>poſitive</hi> is the coalition of the parts rent off into new bodies, or aſſociations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der other Paſtors and Teachers. The formality of ſchiſme conſiſts in the <hi>ſeceſſion</hi> or negative part, though the coalition into new bodies, which was called the ſetting up, <hi>altare contra altare</hi> may make it more obſtinate and pernicious; Now I ſay the cauſe muſt rule us in judging of it. For as it is not the party which ſeparates that makes the Divorce, but the Adulterous party which gives the cauſe. And as (<hi>Mornay</hi> ſaith) it is not the man who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mences or begins the ſuite which makes the trouble, but he that detains the right: So they are the ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks who give the juſt cauſe of ſeparation from them, what a hurry was made in the Church by the <hi>paſchal</hi> controverſie; wherin (<note n="a" place="margin">Tract of ſchiſ. page 5.</note> as one ſaith) both parties might beſchiſmaticks, dividing themſelves aſunder upon ſo triviall a matter, who were
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:159980:23"/> the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> when the ſecond Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> ſet up Images into ſuch honour, and thereby put the Churches into combuſtion? Doubtleſſe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell was the Schiſmaticke? who were the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matics when the <hi>reformed Churches</hi> after all means uſed, were either <hi>driven out,</hi> or <hi>broke off</hi> from the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mornay</hi> of the Church. cap. 10.</note> Pope and his followers, not the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, who departed from them, as the <hi>Romans</hi> had a ſaying, that when the <hi>Gauls</hi> had taken <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Camillus,</hi> with the reſt of the Patriots were at <hi>Veij,</hi> then, though the walls of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtood where they did before, yet <hi>Rome</hi> was not in <hi>Rome</hi> but at <hi>Veij;</hi> I ſhall not meddle with thoſe <hi>Epiſcopal diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in the auncient Churches, commonly called <hi>ſchiſmes,</hi> nor thoſe about the Popedome <note n="d" place="margin">Spalato <hi>lib. 4.</hi> de rep. eccleſ. <hi>cap. 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>thirty in number,</hi> as they are reckoned: Schiſme ſimply and nakedly is a breaking off, or breaking off from the communion of the Church, upon ſuch grounds as have no weight in the word of God to allow them, as namely when <note n="c" place="margin">Schiſma ni fallor eſt eadem opinantem at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eodem ritu co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentem quo cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri, ſolo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectari diſſidio. <hi>Aug.</hi> contra Fauſtum. <hi>lib. 20.</hi> et contra Creſconium grammat.</note> the ſame faith or doctrine in ſubſtantialls is held, and there is accordance and agreement in them: yet through paſſions and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends or fancies, there is offence taken at leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer matters of <hi>fact</hi> or <hi>order,</hi> and ſo the divorce is made for ſuch faults in the yoke-fellow as are farre ſhort of <hi>adultery,</hi> as if the members of any of the ſeven Churches ſhould have ſeparated, becauſe of ſome droſſe in thoſe Golden Candleſticks. The <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſt</hi> who ſeparated upon that principle, that there was not true Church where good and bad were mixt; and that the chaffe in the floore made the wheate uncleane, or that the communion of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:159980:23"/> godly was blaſted and polluted by the mixture of ungodly ones amongſt them, was in open ſchiſme: both in breaking off from the Churches of Chriſt upon that reaſon, and in aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing liberty to erect new Churches, onely which, he called the true Churches of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now for haereſy; it is ſchiſme and ſomwhat more as the Apoſtle implies, and what is that <hi>majus quid</hi> as Tertullian calls it, or that <hi>ſomewhat more,</hi> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is given in that generally received ſaying of <hi>Terome, haereſis perverſum dogma habet</hi> Haereſy goes with a perverſe opinion, or errour in doctrine, which I conceive to be a very truth, (though <note n="d" place="margin">Grotius in 1 Cor. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> affirme that <hi>ex vi vocis</hi> it be <hi>nihil aliud quam ſchiſma</hi>) becauſe the word <hi>haereſy</hi> in all authors, from the firſt uſe of it hath ſignified a ſentence or dogmaticall tenet or aſſertion, as the ſeverall Sects of Philoſophers who differd in their opinions are <note place="margin">i Jamblichus. <hi>lib. 2. cap. 1.</hi>
               </note> called <hi>haereſies</hi> and therefor <hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Jamblichus</hi> haveing written of the life of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> now ſaith he it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines that I ſpeake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> concerning his tenets or opinions, ſo the ſects of <hi>Saducees</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> who differd in opinions are called <hi>haereſies,</hi> and the <note n="f" place="margin">Haereſin Syri vocant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrinam Druſius in <hi>Act. 24. 5.</hi>
               </note> Syriake calls haereſy, <hi>doctrine,</hi> in which ſenſe it muſt be taken. <hi>Acts.</hi> 28. 22. this <hi>haereſy</hi> that is this <hi>doctrine</hi> concerning Chriſt is every where ſpoken againſt or contradicted, and the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> are expreſſe, that theſe haereſies are brought in by <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> and are oppoſite to the <hi>faith,</hi> denying Chriſt Ieſus the Lord and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demdtion. 2. <hi>Pet. 2. 1. Jude.</hi> 3. 4. upon all which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, and that (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> elegantly ſaith) haereſy is a degenerate thing, which ariſes from the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:159980:24"/> corruption and adulterating of the truth (<hi>tanquam caprificus a papauere fici, oleaſter, ex olivae grano &amp;c</hi>) I am cleer enough that in <hi>haereſy</hi> there muſt be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of opinion or doctrine, and ſo the meaning of the Apoſtle in this place of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> is to ſhew, that as there were already ſchiſmes amongſt them, and dividing into parties as their partiality, affection, and ſelfe-reſpects led them, ſo, there muſt be alſo haereſies or errours in doctrine which ſhould <hi>fight againſt the truth</hi> of the Goſpell, &amp; <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize vitious, and filthy luſts</hi> of the fleſh, to which both errours, and luſts there would be ſome that would decline, but thoſe that were approved and ſound-hearted would be made manifeſt among them, and ſo I conclude that haereſy is a renting or tearing the communion of the Church, as it is ſchiſme, and a ſubverting of the doctrine of truth and holineſs as it is haereſy, like ſedition in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, (for ſchiſme as one ſaith is an eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical ſedition) when it is not only made againſt the faults of ſome perſons, or their miſcarriage in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or ſome abuſes in fact, but ariſeth from principles or errours oppoſite and deſtructive to the fundamentall lawes and juſtice of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The ſecond place is that Gal. 5. 19. 20. <hi>The workes of the fleſh are manifeſt which are</hi> adultery fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. &amp;c. <hi>Seditions, hereſies,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tranſlated <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi> Rom. 16. 17. is here tranſlated <hi>ſeditions,</hi> ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or diviſions and haereſies may well be <hi>ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> for <hi>they goe together,</hi> haereſies are workes of the fleſh, <hi>manifeſt</hi> workes of the fleſh, The workes of the fleſh are ſaid to be manifeſt, either becauſe they are the product and fruites of that inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159980:24"/> called <hi>fleſh,</hi> and are the tokens and markes of a carnall man, or becauſe they may be diſcerned and knowne by the <note n="g" place="margin">Mr. Perkin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in Galath 5.</hi>
               </note> light of reaſon and of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſcience, except the light be by ſtrength of luſts extinct, or by the judgement of God darkned or put out. Divines uſually from this place doe prove againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that by fleſh is not onely meant the ſenſuall appetite or inferiour faculties of the Soule, but the higher alſo, as the minde and judgement, becauſe haereſy is an errour of the minde and ſo no doubt it is, though it may be called carnall alſo in reſpect of thoſe fleſhly luſts or ends which carry men thereinto, and are exerciſed under the patronage thereof. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſometime ſaith that in his judgement, it either not at all, or very hardly can be regularly defined <note n="b" place="margin">Aut non omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no aut difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp;c. Aug. ad quod vult deum in proefatione.</note> what makes an haeretick, but he comes very neere it in another place ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee is an haeretick (in my opinion) who for ſome or other temporall profit eſpecially his owne glory or dignity, doth either beget <note n="i" place="margin">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>redendi cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> commodi &amp; maxime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> principatuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſui gratia. &amp;c.</note> or follow falſe and new opinions. The Scripture notion of the word haereſy runs very much this way, and it is to be feared that mens ſelfe ends, wealth, eminency in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts have too much ingrediency into their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in theſe times, the Lord will diſcover and blaſt the doctrine which he hates, and them alſo that hold up ſuch opinions, as are under his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and haply againſt the conſcience alſo, of thoſe that follow them, for their private and unworthy ends.</p>
            <p>The third place is that Titus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 10. 11. <hi>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is an haeretick after the firſt and ſecond ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on reject. Knowing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that is ſuch, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:159980:25"/> ſinneth being condemned of himſelfe.</hi> In the former <hi>verſe</hi> there is an exhortation <hi>to avoid fooliſh queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and genealogies and contentions and ſtrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings about the Law becauſe they are unprofitable and vaine,</hi> and then it followes. A man that is a haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. &amp;c. whence the <note n="a" place="margin">Examen cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurae. <hi>pag. 272. and 280.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Arminians</hi> interpret an hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick to be one that makes contention and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion upon trifling and ſlighty queſtions, who is condemned of himſelfe becauſe he litigates and makes a ſtirre about ſuch things as himſelfe knowes to be of ſmall importance, but I conceive the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not to be ſo ſlighty as they would make it, for it is ſaid of ſuch a one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he is ſubverted, as a Ship that turns up her keele or a houſe when the foundation is turned topſy turvy, and therefore <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 20. where the extreamly deſperate eſtate of a people at laſt caſt, is expreſt, the Greeke ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it by the word uſed in this text. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it is a people turned upſide downe or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, which alſo the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit us cum ſuperior pars in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mam vertitur Avenarius.</hi>
               </note> Hebrew word imports both in this place and elſe where, and ſo haereſy is concluded to be a <hi>ſubverſive</hi> thing and not a peeviſh litigation about ſlight queſtions, as the <hi>Arminians</hi> would put it off, but thus much may be collected from the cohaerence, <hi>that a man may be denominated an haeretick for doctrinall and dogmaticall errours holden and contentiouſly defended and maintained,</hi> and it is obſerved by ſome that wordes of this forme and termination as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do ſignifie an <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> or readineſſe, and ſo the <note n="c" place="margin">Cameron my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothec. cui volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe eſt tueri fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas &amp; erroneas opiniones.</note> word in the text ſignifies, one that with complacency and choyce adheres to ſuch errours, but the greateſt doubt is what is meant by thoſe wordes, <hi>he ſinneth being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:159980:25"/> of himſelfe,</hi> which <note n="d" place="margin">Chriſoſt. in <hi>Titus. 3. 10. 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> refers to the admonitions precedent, for in that ſuch a man hath been admoniſht, he cannot reply in his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> no man hath ſhewed me my er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, no man hath better inſtructed me, and ſo hath his mouth ſtopt and is condemned of <hi>his owne conſcience,</hi> and it is not to be denyed that very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny interpreters both ancient and moderne by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doe underſtand a man that is convinced in his owne conſcience that he erres, and that he goes contrary to his owne light, <hi>ſciens, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens,</hi> but this interpretation is by <note n="e" place="margin">Minus Celſus pag. 13. Eſtius in locum, cum multis aliis.</note> many diſallowd and argued againſt, that moderate and ſweet breath|'d <note n="f" place="margin">De Arrianis. <hi>lib. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salvian</hi> ſpeakeing of the <hi>Arrians</hi> ſaith, <hi>Haeretici ſunt, non ſcientes, apud nos non apud ſe, quod illi nobis, hoc nos illis &amp;c. They are Haereticks but not knowingly,</hi> with us <hi>they are,</hi> but not <hi>with themſelves,</hi> And indeed the word in the text doth not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily carry ſo farre, as that an haeretick is condemned of his owne conſcience, but as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a <hi>man</hi> taught of himſelfe, without a Maſter, ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a <hi>man condemned of himſelfe,</hi> not merely miſled by others to whom he hath given up himſelfe blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, but as one that hath electively taken up and with a fixed ſelf-will is reſolved to perſiſt, in his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and way, which he thinks to be truth, and that he doth Godgood ſervice in holding on in it, there are two things that may be cleerly taken up. 1. That it is made the character of an haeretick to ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe condemned of himſelfe. 2. That another man may know that he is ſubverted and ſins being ſelfe condemned, for 'its ſaid after admonition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him <hi>Knowing that he that is ſuch is ſubverted.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:159980:26"/> &amp;c. But how ſhall this be known? Is it becauſe he ſins againſt common notions or principles within the ken of natures light? This reſtraines haereſy which is a ſubverting of the <hi>faith</hi> onely to that which is contrary to light of nature, which light of nature may bee in ſome particular ſo defaced, like a ſuperſcription on old coyne, that though I may know he ſins, yet he is not convinced in himſelfe. Is it then becauſe he takes an opinion for his luſts ſake and private ends againſt his light and knowledge? Then indeed he ſins becauſe condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of himſelfe, but how can another know it? It reſts therefore that an haeretick rejecting admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be ſaid to be condemned of himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee chuſeth his owne errours, and rejects the truth and ſo <hi>interpretative</hi> that is vertually and by conſequence is condemned of himſelfe, as they who <hi>thruſt away the word from them,</hi> did <hi>judge</hi> themſelves <hi>unworthy of eternall life.</hi> Acts. 13. 46. Here is (as you ſee) an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ſelfe condemning without conviction of conſcience or knowledge of their own ſin in it.</p>
            <p>The fourth place is the Text which we have in hand, and this whole chapter, compared with the Epiſtle of <hi>Iude,</hi> in both which haereſy is graphically deſcribed, as hath before been opend. That which remaines to be done, is the drawing up of that hath been ſaid concerning the meaning of the <hi>word,</hi> or the explication of the <hi>things,</hi> out of the Scriptures alleaged, into a <hi>reſult,</hi> and that is this. The Scripture ſeemes to make haereſy a complicate evill in which there is theſe three things (whether all of <hi>them</hi> eſſentiall ingredients, or ſome of them
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:159980:26"/> be uſuall attendants or concomitants I diſpute not)</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Dogmaticall or doctrinall errour,</hi> even over throwing the faith or <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2. Tim. 2. 18.</hi> Funditas ever. tunt, ſolo equa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> ſubverting the pillars and foundations of the doctrine of Chriſt which <hi>Jude</hi> calls the <hi>common ſalvation</hi> ver. 3. 2. <hi>Seperation from, or renting of the unity and communion of the Church,</hi> ſome time <note n="b" place="margin">Schiſina e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ructat in here. ſin ut non nemo ait.</note> ſchiſme introduces haereſy, when men are <hi>run</hi> out upon peeviſhneſſe of ſpirit or ſome unwarrantable grounds, they commonly <hi>run on</hi> into errour of opinion and doctrine, being caught like a looſe and wandring ſheep, ſeverd from the flock by the wolves which lie in waite for ſuch, ſometimes the ſchiſme followes upon the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of opinion drunke in, and ſo <hi>departure</hi> from the truth, is attended with departure from the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and communion of the Church <hi>Jude</hi> have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſcribed haerenicks, ſaith <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>theſe are they that ſeparate themſelves.</hi> 3. A looſe and carnall courſe taken up and followed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther privately or openly, and that under the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and protection of theſe dogmaticall errours, Their lives are as full of <hi>Athiſme</hi> as their opinions <hi>of blaſphemy or falſe-hand,</hi> all which being laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it appeares that an haereticke's underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; <hi>mind is corrupted,</hi> a good <hi>conſcience</hi> is <hi>thruſt away, his will</hi> electively <hi>adheres to errour</hi> and falſe wayes; <hi>his affections are drowned in ſenſuality</hi> and luſts, he is <hi>ſubverted</hi> and <hi>ſins</hi> being <hi>ſelfe condemned,</hi> either <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Oicumen in tit. 3. 8.</hi>
               </note> formerlly, by his owne conſcience and light yet remaining, or <note n="d" place="margin">Ideo ſibi dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus quia in quo damnatur ſibi eligit Tertull, de proe</note> 
               <hi>virtually</hi> by his voluntary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Gods truth to ſtick to his owne errour, and ſo in concluſion (except the Lord pull him out of the fire by ſome happy hand in the meane
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:159980:27"/> time) hee brings upon himſelfe <hi>ſwift deſtruction.</hi> As touching <hi>pertinacy</hi> or <hi>obſtinacy</hi> which is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by <hi>Divines</hi> put into the definition of haereſie according to that ſaying: <hi>errare poſſum, haereticus eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe nolo,</hi> I ſhall ſay but this, that <hi>obſtinacy</hi> may bee conſidered, either in reſpect of the <hi>crime</hi> of <hi>haereſie,</hi> or of the <hi>cenſure</hi> and rejection of an Haereticke.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the <hi>crime</hi> of <hi>haereſie</hi> two ways. Firſt, that an errour in it ſelfe not haereſie is made haereſie, by <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> as ſome of the Papiſts will have that to be haereſie which is ſtifly holden by any man after the <note n="e" place="margin">Rhemiſts Annot. in <hi>Tit. 3. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>determination</hi> or <hi>admonition</hi> of the Church, when a Councell, or that <hi>tranſcendent</hi> thing called the <hi>Pope</hi> hath defined by the authority of his infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chaire, that ſuch an errour is haereſie, and hath put it under <hi>Anathema,</hi> though <note n="f" place="margin">Error in ſide non ideo haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis quia ab ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia damnatus ſed quia fidei contrarius. <hi>Altenſtaig, &amp;c.</hi> verbo, haereſis &amp; Turre crem, ſumma, <hi>lib. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part. cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> others of them (in my opinion) ſay more rightly, that an errour in faith is <hi>not therefore haereſie, becauſe condemned by the Church:</hi> but becauſe contrary to the faith: or <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that an errour ſubverting the faith is not <hi>haereſie,</hi> unleſſe attended with <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> and that (as I conceive) cannot be ſaid; for as <hi>Conſtancy</hi> in that which is good, as namely <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>juſtice,</hi> doth not make <hi>faith</hi> to be <hi>faith,</hi> or <hi>juſtice</hi> to be <hi>juſtice:</hi> ſo neither doth <hi>obſtinacy</hi> in evill, or <hi>errour,</hi> make that errour to be haereſie; but as vertue is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and rendred more glorious by conſtancy, ſo is haereſie aggravated and made more high by <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy.</hi> The eſſence or nature, and ſo the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of haereſie is not to be meaſured by obſtinacy againſt the deciſion or admonition of the Church, (for then every ſuch obſtinate errour ſhould be hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie) but by the contrariety and oppoſition of it to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:159980:27"/> the principles of faith which are razed or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the <hi>cenſure and rejection</hi> of an <hi>Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> (which rejection, whether it be by a private be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever or by ſentence of the Church I now diſpute not) I ſuppoſe obſtinacy is requiſite: for as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcandalls the rule of proceeding is. <hi>If hee heare not thee,</hi> or <hi>if he heare not the Church:</hi> ſo its ſaid, a man that is an Haereticke, <hi>reject, after the firſt and ſecond admonition;</hi> Contumacy is a common adjunct of ſinne, in order to the finall judgement or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Church in excommunication; In a word, I cannot read thoſe words, <hi>Titus 3. 10. Thus, or in this ſenſe.</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A man that after the firſt and ſecond admonition is an Haereticke,</hi> as if he then became an Haereticke by ſtanding out againſt or after admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but <hi>thus, reject a man haereticall;</hi> after the firſt and ſecond admonition, which argues and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates, that he may be an Haeretick before he bee obſtinate, and ſo obſtinacy is not eſſentiall to the nature or being of haereſie, Though I confeſſe, (and doe ſuggeſt it to your obſervation and ſaddeſt thoughts) that Haeretickes are generally and uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſtricken with obſtinacy,</hi> few of them that runne into this labyrinth doe either ſeeke, or finde the way out; when the vitall parts of faith are putrified and corrupted in any Patient, the recovery is hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe; weigh ſeriouſly that expreſſion or marke ſet on <hi>theſe very men</hi> by <hi>Iude,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>Trees twice dead, plucked up by the rootes;</hi> when do you ſee ſuch a tree recover life and fruit? Its a hard reſcue to fetch a man off that is priſoner to an erring conſcience, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if he be fetter'd by both legs, his judgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:159980:28"/> captivated by errour, and his affections enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by luſts; we muſt doe our duty, and of <hi>ſome have compaſſion,</hi> and others of them <hi>ſave with feare:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſnatching them out of the fire.</hi> Jude, <hi>verſe</hi> 22. 23. Though they complaine of violence offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their <hi>liberty,</hi> when they are pul'd out of the fire. For (as <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> qui ſervat idem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cidenti Horat.</note> the ſaying is) <hi>hee that ſaves a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, hath no more thankes for his labour then if he kill'd him.</hi> It is a matter of wonder and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement to ſee men of eminent parts and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of great reputation for Religion, captivated, carried away, and made prey of, by ſenſeleſſe and abſurd fancies and opinions: but that wee know there are no deluſions or lies, but are ſtrong when God delivers a man up to them in way of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for not receiving the truth with love thereof. The Lord give us to receive his truth with fear and trembling, and make us thankfull (whom in this time of <hi>wantonneſſe</hi> (as ſome call it) or rather <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> of opinions, hee hath kept from ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of faith, and made to ſtand upright when men that have lived ſtrictly and religiouſly (as <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chryſ. Epiſtola 4. ad Olymp.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaid of <hi>Pelagius</hi>) ſeem to warp and to be drawn awry.</p>
            <p>Having thus farre laid open the nature and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of haereſie by the Scriptures, I ſhould now come to the uſe of all: but that in few words I deſire to put you in minde in what notion the word haereſie hath paſſed amongſt men in common acceptation, and that I ſhall doe in theſe two words.</p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> or <hi>Scholaſticall</hi> acceptation is this: <note n="a" place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rem. ſum. lib. 4.</note> Haereſie is an errour or aſſertion contrary to the faith in points fundamentall or momentous,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:159980:28"/> holden or maintain'd by a man profeſſing the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith: this they call <hi>ſimple</hi> haereſie, and ſuch a one an Haereticke: <hi>licet ab eccleſia non receſſerit,</hi> though (ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">In Gal. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome</hi>) hee doth not ſeparate or make ſeceſſion from the Church: and though hee cannot be blemiſht with wickedneſſe morall, or in converſation. All momentous truths are not ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly ſo called fundamentall; there are truths (as I may ſay) of ſecond and third magnitude; like ſtones in a building which be next unto, or upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; what theſe are which are preciſely funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, and what is the boundary of them, and by what certaine meaſure they muſt be meaſured, if it exceed not my skill to determine (as I dare not ſay but it may) yet it is a worke beyond my time. This only I ſay to the point in hand, That the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis ratio</hi> or nature of haereſie as it is diſtinguiſht from ſchiſme and fleſhly luſts, is rightly ſtated to conſiſt in an errour or aſſertion, contrary to, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the faith, and the degree of pravity in the errour, is correſpondent to the degree of impor tance of the truth that's deſtroyed by it ordenied.</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>vulgar,</hi> and indeed <hi>abuſive</hi> acceptation of the word, is an infamy or reproach which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally men flinge in the face of others at random, that are not of their opinion: and its too true (as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man ſaith) that <hi>haereſie</hi> and <hi>ſchiſme</hi> are two the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall ſcare-crowes, many times ſet up to ſcare people and affright them. The <hi>ſtrongeſt party</hi> of the two commonly cries out of <hi>haereſie:</hi> the <hi>weakeſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> cry out of <hi>perſecution,</hi> ſo the <hi>Papiſt</hi> puts a marke or brand of haereticall pravity upon, and calls all Haeretickes, who are oppoſite to their <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Spalato. lib.</hi> 1 cap 10.</note> falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:159980:29"/> or filthy luſts; Haereſie was taken in a large ſenſe, when the <note n="d" place="margin">L. <hi>Cooke</hi> his Inſtitutes.</note> 
               <hi>Lollards</hi> were indicted for haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, becauſe they held it not meritorious to goe in pilgrimage to Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> or <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> or when <hi>Virgilius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Saltzburg</hi> was condemned for the haereſie of holding that there were <hi>Antipodes;</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Apology, <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tells K. <hi>Iames</hi> that for all his beleeving <hi>the Scriptures,</hi> the <hi>three Creeds,</hi> the <hi>foure</hi> great and generall <hi>Councells,</hi> yet he might be an Haereticke: and his meaning was, becauſe the <hi>Popes infallibility</hi> or <hi>ſupremacy</hi> was not in any of the Kings <hi>Creeds.</hi> As the intollerable abuſe of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication formerly, made no man to value it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the price at which he could buy it off; ſo the abuſe of this name, and throwing it about at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, makes it not regarded, which yet is a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing in it ſelfe, and bringing ſwift deſtruction; It hath been ſtretcht too farre to be a brand ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing true beleevers, and to ſcare men from pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the trueth by making it odious, and it is ſhriveled and ſhrunke up too much, even almoſt to nothing by ſuch as are affraid to hit themſelves by defining it: but is <hi>there not ſuch a thing?</hi> is there not <hi>ſuch a damnable ſin?</hi> why then doe ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſins as the ſin againſt <hi>the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the ſin of <hi>haereſie,</hi> lye like a <hi>terra incognita</hi> undiſcovered, unpreacht againſt? Seeing there is to be found in Scripture, eſpecially in the <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> Epiſtles, ſo much ſaid in deſcription of, and for caution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt damnable haereſies and doctrines, and the falſe teachers which privily bring them in, and bring upon themſelves and many that follow their pernicious wayes, ſuch fearfull deſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:159980:29"/>
            <p>That which now remains is to draw up that which hath been ſaid into matter of uſe and application.</p>
            <p>And firſt let me ſpeak to you all, who profeſſethe <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> trueth of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you would be <hi>Proteſtants once again,</hi> by declaring your ſelves againſt the <hi>heterodoxies</hi> &amp; dangerous errors of the preſent times, for the infection ſpreads by reaſon of many that goe abroad with running ſores upon them; and if the Apoſtle, <hi>when hee gave all diligence</hi> to write to beleevers <hi>of the common ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> thought <hi>it needfull for him to write to them, and exhort them that they ſhould earneſtly contend for the faithonce delivered to the Saints,</hi> upon this ground and reaſon <hi>that there were certain men crept in unawares, &amp;c.</hi> Jude 3. 4. You cannot thinke it impertinent and unſeaſonable at this time to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to the ſame <hi>earneſt contending</hi> for the faith, for you are beſet with danger on all ſides, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion is epidemicall, many are diſtracted with <hi>here is</hi> Chriſt, and <hi>there is</hi> Chriſt, and are miſ-led into pernicious wayes: yea even ſome that ſeemed to be good eares of come are mil-dewd and almoſt blaſted, I doe therefore exhort you to conſider the danger, as you may eaſily ſumme it up from that which hath been ſaid, for you have heard<hi rend="sup">i</hi> 
               <hi>that</hi> there <hi>ſhall be falſe Teachers</hi> amongſt you, weneed not ſay there, <hi>ſhall be,</hi> but more ſuitable to our owne condition wee may ſay, <hi>There are</hi> as its ſaid, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 4. <hi>many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world;</hi> you ſee they are <hi>gone out,</hi> I would we might ſee that they were <hi>come in againe.</hi> 2. <hi>That</hi> theſe are they who bring in <hi>damnable haereſies,</hi> they <hi>goe out</hi> to bring theſe in, they are ring-leaders, or (as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:159980:30"/> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid of Philoſophers) <hi>the patriarchs of hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies.</hi> 3. <hi>That</hi> they bring in theſe damnable haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies <hi>privily,</hi> they ſpawn firſt in <hi>quaeries</hi> or plauſible beginnings (the greateſt Crocodile did at firſt lye in an egge <note n="a" place="margin">Franzius hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria animali um.</note> 
               <hi>Paulo majus anſerino,</hi> little bigger then a gooſe-egge) <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 15.</note> themſelves are <hi>transformed as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of righteouſneſſe:</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 3. Rom. 16. 18.</note> their words are compoſed and good, their ſpeeches are faire, their artifice is <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 4. 14.</note> full of ſleight and cunning craftineſſe, and therefore they creepe at unawares not onely into houſes, but into mens boſomes alſo. 4. <hi>That</hi> hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies are damnable and deſtructive poiſon, though given in honey, they ariſe and are made up <hi>coede Scripturarum</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith) by <hi>felling downe the goodly timber of the holy Scriptures;</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16.</note> wreſted to the <hi>deſtruction of them that wreſt them;</hi> they <hi>turne grace into laſciviouſneſſe; deny the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, overthrow the faith, ſubvert the ſoule, carry men down the ſtream of luſt and liberty,</hi> and ſo bring <hi>ſwift deſtruction.</hi> 5. <hi>That</hi> many ſhall follow theſe pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wayes, <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 16. 18.</note> the ſimple are deceived, the learned are given up to <note n="g" place="margin">2 Theſ 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrong deluſions,</hi> the unſtable are carried about like children with every <note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>wind of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> Thoſe that by profeſſion of the truth had eſcaped the pollutions of the world, are againe <note n="i" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>entangled and overcome,</hi> and ſo the <hi>latter end of many</hi> (that are carried away either by ſpeciouſneſſe of errour or liberty of luſt) is <hi>worſe then the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> 6. <hi>That</hi> the laſt times ſhall be moſt of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted with theſe pernicious errours. <note n="k" place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Jude 17. 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeaketh expreſly,</hi> that in the <hi>latter times</hi> ſome ſhal depart from the faith, <hi>giving heed to ſeducing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles have foretold</hi> that there ſhall bee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:159980:30"/> 
               <hi>mockers in the laſt time:</hi> and by this (ſaith <note n="m" place="margin">1 John 2. 18.</note> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) we know that it is the <hi>laſt time</hi> becauſe there are many <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> and wee may very well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the laſt times, not onely the times of the Goſpell in generall, but the time of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> declining as well as of his ariſing and growth. <hi>The laſt of the laſt times:</hi> For as the laſt times of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh Church</hi> (after it had ſhaken off the <hi>captivity</hi> and <hi>idolatry</hi>) were peſter'd and infeſted moſt of all with haereſies untill Chriſt came with a new doctrine of the Goſpell, and untill the deſolution of the frame of that Church: ſo the laſt dayes of Goſpell Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches having ſhaken off the ſecond <hi>Babyloniſh capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity</hi> and <hi>idolatry,</hi> ſhall be infeſted with theſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous errours and haereſies, and haply untill the very ſecond comming of Chriſt, or at leaſt untill he ſhall gloriouſly declare himſelf in the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the beaſt and <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> and in the calling of the Jewes.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being laid together doe cry aloud unto you, to conſider your danger, and to hearken to the frequent inculcations of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in their Epiſtles, in <hi>almoſt all their</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> deſcribing falſe teachers to bee like the <hi>Serpent</hi> that beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> branding them with the name of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres, Balaam, falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers, miniſters of Sathan, &amp;c.</hi> ſtigmatizing their doctrins with the names of <hi>damnable haereſies, doctrines of Devills, &amp;c.</hi> Fortifying Chriſtians with effectuall arguments and exhortations againſt the impreſſions and infections of ſuch poyſonous errours. And if you looke upon thoſe Epiſtles which were ſent from heaven to the <hi>ſeven Churches,</hi> you ſhall finde
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:159980:31"/> that the greateſt part of thoſe comminations in them contained, are thundred forth againſt <hi>haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> or doctrinall errours, maintaining or cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as I may call them) <hi>haereticall luſts,</hi> there wee finde them <note n="b" place="margin">Revel. 2. 2.</note> that ſaid they were <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but were <hi>lyers,</hi> the <note n="c" place="margin">cap. 2. 9. 14. 15. 20. 24.</note> 
               <hi>blaſphemy</hi> of ſuch as ſaid they were <hi>Jews,</hi> but were the <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> the <hi>doctrine of</hi> Balaam, the <hi>doctrine of the Nicolaitans,</hi> the <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and ſeducing of</hi> Jezebel, <hi>the depths of Sathan, &amp;c.</hi> The Churches are commended, or the Angels of thoſe Churches, who found out theſe <hi>diſguiſed ſeducers,</hi> and kept the truth uninfected by them, and thoſe Angels or Churches blamed which <note n="d" place="margin">Revel. 2. 15.</note> had them <note n="e" place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> and ſuffered them in their boſome. Theſe things I offer to your ſerious and ſad conſideration, you have not made uſe of the point, as ſoone as you have ſaid <hi>The Miniſter railes.</hi> Its not my meaning to poure out all this that hath beene ſaid upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry errour either preacht or followed in our times: but to ſhew you that falſe teachers and haereſies <hi>muſt be</hi> and <hi>ſhall be</hi> in the Goſpel Churches: and to put you in minde what the Scripture ſaith concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, and how much you are concerned to looke about you: for I obſerve that men are not ſo jealous over themſelves, or ſo affraid of <hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their</hi> minds as they ought to be, nor ſo ſenſible of ſin in intellectuall errours as in morall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet we know diſeaſes in the head are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall too: and that a fiſh begins to corrupt and ſtink in the head and ſo throughout; <hi>corrupt manners</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually and naturally follow upon <hi>corrupt minds;</hi> they that are not <hi>ſound in the faith,</hi> no wonder if they be not <hi>ſound</hi> in the <hi>feare,</hi> and in the <hi>wayes of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:159980:31"/> God,</hi> whither will this new <hi>ſcepticiſme</hi> come and into what will it be reſolved? but <hi>into Athieſme,</hi> when men begin to fall; we ſee by experience, that many fall from <hi>ſtory</hi> to <hi>ſtory</hi> till they come to the very bottom, And therefore I exhort and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you all to that which the ſcripture exhorts and in joynes upon Chriſtians, who are in danger of being ſeduced by falſe teachers or their doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, and that is, <hi>to try the ſpirits</hi> whether they are of God. 1. <hi>John. 4. 1. To contend</hi> for the faith once delivered <hi>Jude. 3. To beware</hi> leſt you be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with the <hi>errour of lawleſſe men</hi> 2. Pet. 3. 17. <hi>To turne away from</hi> ſuch as creep into houſes <hi>and lead captive</hi> ſilly women, 2. <hi>Tim. 3. 5. 6. To avoid fooliſh</hi> queſtions which are unprofitable and vaine <hi>Titus. 3. 9. To hold faith and a good conſcience.</hi> 1. Tim. 1. 19. <hi>To continue in the things that you have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and been aſſured of out of the word of God, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 14. And laſtly <hi>If there come any unto you,</hi> and bring not this doctrine receive him not into your houſe neither ſay to him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 2. <hi>Epiſtle. of John.</hi> 10. 11. For he that bids him god ſpeed <hi>is partaker of his evill deeds,</hi> where the Apoſtle ſuppoſes that falſe teachers are men of evill deeds, beſides their falſe doctrines, or that indeed their falſe doctrine <hi>is evill deeds</hi> in the plurall number, and therefore not to be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted off as <hi>a thing of the minde</hi> or <hi>mentall mistake</hi> onely, you ſee that to countenance or encourage ſuch teachers is to be partaker of their evill deeds, and whatſoever credit you will give to the report of <note n="f" place="margin">lib. 3. <hi>cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> concerning <hi>John</hi> his leaping out of the bath from <hi>Cerinthus</hi> or <hi>Polycarp</hi> his refuſeal of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:159980:32"/> his acquaintance, yet, the obſervation which he makes uponthoſe reports or hiſtories, is to be taken notice of <hi>that the Apoſtles and their followers, would</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tantum Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toli &amp; eorum diſcipu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i &amp;c. Iren lib. 3. <hi>cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not ſo much as verbo tenus communicate with any of them that had adulterated the truth,</hi> how much leſſe ſhould private Chriſtians cloſe with ſuch ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers who are more likely to pull them into the water, then they to pull them out, Naturally wee are tinder too apt to take fire by their ſparkes, he that fiſhes with an <hi>haereticall bait</hi> may haply catch more in a moneth, than ſome godly Miniſter ſhall bring to Chriſt with all his travell and paines, as long as he lives, for <hi>he hath the advantage of the bait</hi> and therein lies the odds of ſucceſſe between preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of errour and preaching of the truth, I maruell (ſaith the Apoſtle) that you are <hi>ſo ſoone removed from him,</hi> that called you into the grace of Chriſt, <hi>unto another goſpell.</hi> Gal. 1. 6. there was the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that they were removed ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the Apoſtles wonder may be ours alſo, wee have been a people of as powerfull godlineſſe, as any in the world; practicall divinity was impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to a great height of cleareneſſe and ſweetneſſe but I feare that I may truely ſay <hi>we were beſt in worſt times,</hi> wee held our cloake in the winde and now are laying it off in the ſun, A miſerable decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the life and power of godlineſſe is come to paſſe within theſe few yeares, our practicals, our inward and cloſe wayes of walking with God in faith and love, are ſublimed into fancies and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour out into fumes of new opinions, and which is worſt of all, we take this dropſy to be growth, and conceive our ſelves to be more ſpirituall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:159980:32"/> becauſe more ayry and notionall. The Lord humble us for our declenſions and ſwervings from the <note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 3.</note> 
               <hi>end of the commandement</hi> (which is love out of a pure heart and of a good conſcience and of faith unfained) and <hi>for our turnings aſide to vaine ianglings,</hi> The beſt way of fortification of our ſelves againſt the allurements and aſſaults of falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is 1. To be grounded in the principles of the doctrines of Chriſt, or elſe we ſhall eaſily be tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled up and downe like looſe ſtones that lie not faſt in the building upon the foundation. 2. To ſtudy and adhere unto the doctrine which is <note n="h" place="margin">1 Tim 1. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to godlineſſe,</hi> practicall and edifying truths, which draw up the heart into acquaintance and communion with God, and draw it out in love and obedience to him, <hi>For its good that the heart be ſtabliſht with grace,</hi> Heb. 13. 9. 3. To hold faith and a good conſcience 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19. for if we <hi>thruſt away a good conſcience</hi> by entertaining baſe luſts and ends, the ſhipwrack of faith will follow. 4. To pray for confirmation and eſtabliſhment by the hand of God, for as it is not a <hi>ſtrong conſtitution</hi> that is a protection <hi>againſt the plague,</hi> ſo neither is it parts and learning which ſecure us from beleeving lies and deluſions. Its a mercy for which we are not enough thankfull, that God keeps any of us ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upright when others ſhrink awry, or that wee are enabled to diſcerne between truth and errour, and to ſtand for the one, and withſtand the other; when ſo many that have driven a great trade of profeſſion are broken and turned bankerupts.</p>
            <p>5. To keep as a treaſure thoſe truths wherein you have formerly found comfort, and which have
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:159980:33"/> been atteſted and confirmed to you by your owne experience, ſit upon thoſe flowers ſtill and ſucke their freſh honey every day. A Chriſtian very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly parts with thoſe truths that have been ſealed up to his experience, <hi>but its no wonder that a man ſhould loſe that out of his head which he never had in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To thoſe that <hi>bring in</hi> or <hi>follow</hi> theſe pernicious <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> wayes of damnable haereſy, you ſhall ſee the crop which you ſhall reap, <hi>ſwift deſtruction,</hi> you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judgement which <hi>ſlumbers not.</hi> It will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to you to <hi>wreſt the Scriptures. 2. Pet. 5. 16. and to make merchandiſe of mens ſoules for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ends. 2. Pet. 2. 3. <hi>To corrupt the mindes of men</hi> from the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> that is in Chriſt. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3. and to <hi>cauſe diviſions</hi> and ſcandalls</hi> Rom. 16. 17. are things which will coſt you deare, lay to heart the terrible expreſſions of wrath which are fulminated againſt ſuch men in Scripture, There may be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in opinion, betweene them that are godly, which are not inconſiſtent, with the peace of the Churches and for which its unlawfull <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(as the hiſtorian ſaith) to make butter and cheeſe of one another,</hi> Its a diſcreet rule which is laid downe by one <note n="a" place="margin">Conradas Bergius. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictamine, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Si non idem ſentimus de veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate at ſaltem de pondere</hi> If we cannot agree <hi>upon the truth</hi> of every queſtion or point of divinity yet at leaſt lets be agreed <hi>concerning the weight</hi> and moment thereof, ſo as not to make as great a ſtirr about a <hi>tile</hi> of the houſe, as if it were a <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtone,</hi> nor erect new parties or Churches upon every leſſer variation; but to contend for, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a <hi>liberty</hi> of profeſſing or publiſhing ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:159980:33"/> as overthrow the faith and <hi>ſubvert the ſoule</hi> under the name of <hi>liberty of conſcience</hi> can be no other then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 2. Tim. 3. 9. <hi>a manifeſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or madneſſe.</hi> Is this liberty any part of <hi>Chriſts pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe?</hi> Hath he made men free to ſin and deny him that bought them? what yoake of bondage doth this liberty free us from? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 1. ſhould we claime <hi>a liberty</hi> of being in <hi>bondage</hi> to errour? or promiſe to men a liberty of being ſervants to corruption, which the falſeteachers in effect did 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 19. God hath (as one ſaith) reſerved to himſelfe as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative three things. <hi>Ex nihilo creare, futura prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere, conſcientijs dominari. To create out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to foretell things to come, to have dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſcience,</hi> and it is true that while a thing is within, in the conſcience, its out of mans reach, but when 'its acted and comes abroad then it comes into <hi>mans juriſdiction</hi> and is cognizable <hi>in foro hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano,</hi> God onely is judge of thoughts, men alſo are judges of actions, Its a great miſtake and of very ill conſequence to imagine that a man is alwayes bound to act or practice according to the light or judgement of conſcience though rightly informed <hi>in theſi,</hi> for then I ſee not, that there can be any place for that rule given by the Apoſtle. Rom: 14. 22. <hi>Haſt thou faith? have it to thy ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,</hi> Truth it ſelfe though <hi>never to be denyed</hi> yet is not <hi>alwayes to be declared,</hi> for the hurt or ſcandall may be greater, then an inſeaſonable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or practice of that which is in it ſelfe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may be worth, but the miſtake is yet more groſſe to imagine that an <hi>erring conſcience is</hi> a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient protection or warranty for an evill act. Its
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:159980:34"/> ſin to goe againſt an erring conſcience, (<hi>Stante dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamine</hi>) as its ſin <hi>to raviſh and force awhore.</hi> Its ſin alſo to act according to the dictate of an erring conſcience as <hi>to committ adul tery with conſent.</hi> To make conſcience the finall judge of actions, is to wipe out the hand writing of the word of God, which doth condemne many times, thoſe things which conſcience juſtifies, yea and men alſo may paſſe juſt judgement on deluſions or lyes though thoſe that vent them doe beleeve them for truths; If <hi>conſcience</hi> be <hi>warrant</hi> enough for <hi>practices</hi> and <hi>opinions,</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>conſcience</hi> be a ſufficient <hi>licence</hi> to <hi>vent</hi> or <hi>act them,</hi> I cannot ſee but the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories either of <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi> may ſhut up their Shop, and bee reſolved into the judicatory of every mans private conſcience. And put the caſe that the Magiſtrate ſhould conceive himſelfe bound in conſcience to draw forth his authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt falſe teachers, or their damnable haereſies, and (upon that ſuppoſed errour) ſhould challenge a liberty of <hi>judging,</hi> as wee doe of <hi>acting,</hi> would our liberty give us any eaſe ſo long as he had his, and were it not better for him to <hi>judge</hi> and for us to <hi>walke</hi> by a knowne rule? and if we ſhould ſay that his liberty of judging is unlawfull, it is as eaſy for him to ſay that our liberty of preaching or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing errours, is ſo too.</p>
            <p>To you that are Miniſters of the word, that you would draw forth the ſword of the Spirit againſt theſe ſpirits of errour, as not onely the duty you owe to Gods truth and mens ſoules requireth, but alſo the preſſing examples of the Apoſtles doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine you; let not the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:159980:34"/> offices,</hi> be denyed by <hi>falſe teachers</hi> and <hi>by your ſilence too,</hi> and the Lord grant that it may not be ſaid of you as of the Miniſters of <hi>Epheſus</hi> Acts. 20. 30. <hi>alſo of your owne ſelves ſhall men ariſe ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things to draw away Diſciples after them. Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> ſaid of ſome <hi>middle-region</hi> men in thoſe times, that they were <hi>Luther anunculi halfe or dough-baked Lutherans;</hi> Let us not halt between two opinions but be valiant for the truth. He is but halfe a good Sheepheard that feeds the ſheep in good paſture, but defends them not from the wolves; It belongs to you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Titus. 1. 11. to ſtop their mouths</hi> that is by conviction as is plaine by the ninth verſe as Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 34. Stopt the <hi>Sadduces</hi> mouths by ſilencing their arguments. They wil tell you that arguments of <hi>vre ſeca, fire &amp; faggot</hi> are not fit arguments for <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that their minds ought to be <hi>enlightned,</hi> not their bodies <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and the truth is, the <hi>keys</hi> are given to <hi>Peter</hi> not the ſword, He uſurps that without authority, <hi>the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, Malchus</hi> eare is not to be cut off by us. But wil they that plead ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from violence, ſuffer &amp; endure the word of conviction? will they afford their ears &amp; patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beare the examination of their errours? I fear they will not; ſuch is their love to &amp; their <hi>pleropho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of errour,</hi> Nay will they not rather caſt dirt upon the Miniſtery, and uſe all ſtratagems to undermine it, decrying their <hi>calling</hi> and their <hi>lively-hood</hi> or <hi>tithes</hi> which among all their deſtructive errours muſt needs be confeſſed to bee <hi>a ſaveing doctrine,</hi> whatſoever be the event, you that are Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters muſt venture into the Lions mouth to ſave a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:159980:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:159980:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:159980:36"/> ſheepe, and aſſert and vindicate the truth of God from being taken captive by errour: for if either his trueth or his people be loſt by your default, the account will be heavy.</p>
            <p>As I began, ſo I ſhall conclude with you (the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> houſe) every one ſees what height we are come unto. <hi>Arrius</hi> in <hi>Alexand.</hi> was but as one ſpark, a little water at firſt would have quench'd that fire which afterward ſet almoſt all the world in flames, I ſee by <hi>your order</hi> for keeping of this ſolemne day, that you take notice of the growth of <hi>errour, haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> and <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> I would you had taken ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the beginnings of them. If you take notice of theſe as a judgement upon us, then ſearch out the ſin for which this judgement comes. If you take notice of them as our ſin, then let every man labour to owne it ſo farre as by participation it is made his owne, that ſo we may be truly humbled, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our Vowes and Covenants to owne and ſtand up for the truth of God, againſt all invaſions of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and haereſie; you as <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> we as <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, all</hi> as men that <hi>have ſoules to be ſaved or loſt.</hi> Its a good rule, <hi>In eo ſerviunt reges deo, in quo non poſſunt illi ſervire niſi ut reges, Kings and Princes,</hi> and indeed all magiſtrates <hi>doe therein ſerve God, wherein they cannot ſerve him but as Magiſtrates:</hi> we are exhorted to pray for <hi>Kings and all that are in authority, that wee may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 2.</p>
            <p>There is (as Divines diſtinguiſh) <hi>ſimple</hi> haereſie and <hi>complicate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simple haereſie</hi> is an opinion or aſſertion holden and maintained contrary to, and ſubverſive of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:159980:36"/> faith by one that profeſſes the Chriſtian Religion: <hi>Complicate haereſie</hi> is that which is attended with <hi>ſchiſme, ſedition, blaſphemy,</hi> where one opinion lyes with another, and begets a new baſtard: a new mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter growing up into a multiformity more &amp; more, until it break forth into ſuch dangerous ſymptoms as the fore-named.</p>
            <p>The ſchiſmaticall Haereticke upon his opinion breaks off from the communion of the Church, and runs out into ſeparation, ſetting up his <hi>new light</hi> (as he calls it) in a <hi>new candleſtick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>blaſphemous Haereticke</hi> ſtrikes through the name of the great and glorious God, or his truth with deſpightfull reproaches not to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſeditious Haereticke</hi> troubles the peace of the Church and State, as an army is troubled by Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineers.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſeducing Haereticke</hi> panders to his bed all hee can, and goes up and down to vent his poyſon to the infection of others, privily bringing in damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble haereſies.</p>
            <p>There is a great conteſt about <hi>ſimple haereſie</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it come under your ſword or no in reſpect of capitall puniſhment. The <note n="o" place="margin">Vide 18. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumenta Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranorum apud Conradum. <hi>Bergium</hi> de hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſi.</note> 
               <hi>Lutherans</hi> are negative and ſo are very many others, <hi>Haereticidium ob ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicem aut nudam haereſin nemo noſtrûm ſimpliciter aſſeruit.</hi> None of us (ſay they) <note n="a" place="margin">Cenſura in cap. 24.</note> have aſſerted haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticide or capitall puniſhment for ſimple haereſie. And <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſc. de Serve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith of <hi>Servetus, vel ſola modeſtia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſſet vitam redimere,</hi> that he might <hi>have ſaved his life had he been but modeſt.</hi> And to ſuch I wiſh light and not fire, let bloudy Papiſts only have this brand
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:159980:37"/> of cruelty upon them to confute errours by fire and faggot.</p>
            <p>For the blaſphemous and ſeditious Haeretickes, both <note n="c" place="margin">Haereticum ſedittoſum &amp; blaſphemum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitali ſupplicio dignum nemo ex noſtris facile impugnabit. Tota quaeſtio eſt de haeretico ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici. <hi>Meiſnerus</hi> Philoſ. ſob ſect 2 cap. 4.</note> Lutherans and others of the Reformed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do agree that they may be puniſhed capitally, that is for their blaſphemy or ſedition; but the <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Schlichtingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> pro Secino contra <hi>Meiſneru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> page 457.</note> 
               <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> ſtands out herealſo, and denies it; alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the puniſhment of falſe Prophets in the old Teſtament was <hi>ſpeciali jure</hi> by ſpeciall law gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and therefore you muſt not looke (ſaith the <hi>Socinian</hi>) into the olde Teſtament for a rule of proceeding againſt falſe Prophets and blaſphemers: Nor (ſaith <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> de Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veto in opuſc. <hi>Catharinus</hi> in 3 Titus 10.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Catharinus</hi>) can you find in the new Teſtament any precept for the puniſhment of Theeves, Traytors, Adulterers, Witches, murtherers and the like, and yet they may, or at leaſt ſome of them bee capitally puniſht: for the Goſpell deſtroys not the juſt lawes of civill policy or Common-wealths; but I will not enter upon the debate of this point, neither bringing in the Scriptures or reaſons for it, nor anſwering the arguments brought againſt it, of which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments this I ſuggeſt (by the way) to your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that ſome of them doe even <hi>ſhip in one bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome the morall duties commanded in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the typicall ceremonies or ſhadowes. Some of them</hi> doe make <note n="a" place="margin">Which <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> denies not as to Haereticks or ſuch as keep not the faith, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. 9. &amp;</hi> 70.</note> againſt Eccleſiaſticall cenſures as well as civill, and <hi>ſome of them</hi> doe carry further then haply they are intended, even to take off civil puniſhments of ſinnes againſt the <hi>ſecond Table alſo:</hi> neither doe I ſee any juſt reaſon, that if the office of a Magiſtrate have any place in the matters of the <hi>firſt Table,</hi> he can puniſh <hi>ſedition,</hi> which is againſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:159980:37"/> his owne name or dignity, and ſtand ſtill and looke on with his hands tied, whiles the name and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the great God is openly traduced or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>ſeducing Haereticke,</hi> he is to be prohibited and reſtrained: you will not ſuffer a man that hath a running <hi>plague-ſore</hi> to go abroad to infect, though his ſhutting up be not in way of puniſhment, as if hee was puniſht becauſe hee hath the ſore, but in way of prevention of contagion, as the reſtraint of the Leper was. You pull downe <hi>another mans houſe and that juſtly</hi> when 'tis on fire to prevent the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the whole <hi>Towne:</hi> one way to put out the fire in the Oven, is to ſhut it up. Many errours and haereſies would die of themſelves if they had not free vent. <hi>Falſi doctores ſathanae lenones</hi> ſaith <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin:</hi> Falſe teachers are the Devils panders; would you ſuffer <hi>panders</hi> to come into your houſes &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licit the chaſtity of your children? would you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Mountebanks</hi> to ſell poiſon upon a ſtage, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the bodies and lives of people? This the <note n="b" place="margin">Examen cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurae, page 285.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants</hi> in ſcorne call our <hi>palmarium argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> but it is not to be deſpiſed as if it was void of reaſon. You that are Chriſtian Magiſtrates ſhould not forget the ſoules of them that live under your ſhadow. There is a <note n="c" place="margin">Minus Celſus in diſputatione de haereticis, &amp;c. pag. 194. &amp;c.</note> learned man who argues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the puniſhing of Haereticks <hi>with death,</hi> and pitches upon this as the <hi>ſolida, vera, certa, ratio,</hi> the ſolid, true, and certain reaſon why other flagitious offenders are to be puniſht, but not Haereticks: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe haereſie (ſaith he) is the <hi>errour of a depraved minde,</hi> an intellectuall errour: but other morall vices ariſe from a <hi>depraved and corrupt will,</hi> and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:159980:38"/> the error of the underſtanding is not (ſaith hee) to be puniſht with death, but that it is to be reſtrained from ſpreading and infecting, the compariſons which he brings in doe fully ſignify. For you would not (ſaith hee) put a Phyſitian to death as a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer who upon meere miſtake gives his patient a potion of poyſon in ſtead of good medicine, nor a mad man that breaks out and kills and ſlaies ſuch as he meets with, becauſe this proceeds from laeſion of his underſtanding, though I doe not concur with this ſuppoſition that haereſie is a a meere act of the underſtanding: for it hath its denomination from the act of the will <hi>chooſing</hi> the errour: yet thus farre I goe with it, that ſuch pretended Phyſitians as hold that to be wholſome which is poiſon, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter it to their Patients, are not to bee <hi>licenſed to practiſe,</hi> nor ſuch mad men ſuffered to be looſe to <hi>exerciſe their fury;</hi> damnable haereſies can never be prevented, if falſe teachers may have liberty to bring them in. Its one thing to ſuffer <hi>Jewes, Turkes, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Haeretickes,</hi> to live in the kingdome or City, and another thing to give them liberty or freedome of Trade, to open their ſhop and call in Cuſtomers to buy their deſtructive wares; <hi>Thou haſt them</hi> that hold the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> Revel. 2. 15. <hi>Thou ſuffereſt</hi> that woman <hi>Jezebel</hi> which calls her ſelfe a <hi>Propheteſſe,</hi> to <hi>teach</hi> and to ſeduce my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, was a ſore charge laid by Chriſt upon thoſe Churches.</p>
            <p>Nor is it the Pulpit which can keep off the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whiles the poiſon is carried up and downe in books, and cryed at mens doors every day, in which there are many ſtrange doctrines going abroad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:159980:38"/> faced, and ſome more ſtrange which goe vailed, and dropt into the Reader by inſinuation, there ſeeme to be very ſtrange dreams about the manner of Chriſts being in the Saints, and Gods being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in their fleſh, and about the Kingdome of the Saints, and the licking of the duſt of their feete by the world. There are myſteries if the world was ripe for them; I take notice of one thing in a late book which hath a very ill aſpect, brought in by way of enquiry, what is meant by the word <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> when it is aſſerted, that the denying of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be the <hi>word of God,</hi> ſhould be holden <hi>worthy of death.</hi> For ſaith the Author, either the <hi>Engliſh Scriptures,</hi> or <hi>Scriptures in Engliſh,</hi> are meant by the word <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and Greeke Copies or originalls. <hi>The former cannot bee meant</hi> with reaſon, becauſe God did not ſpeake to his Prophets and Apoſtles in the Engliſh tongue: nor doth the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlation agree in all things with the originall or the true ſenſe of it; <hi>Nor the latter,</hi> for the greateſt part of men in the Kingdome doe not underſtand or know them. If this <hi>dilem</hi> be good, what is become of the <hi>certaine foundation</hi> of our <hi>hope</hi> or <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>comfort;</hi> how can we <hi>ſearch</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> without going firſt to ſchoole to learne <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek.</hi> Its well knowne that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelfe and the Apoſtles doe uſually cite the <hi>Greek</hi> tranſlation or <hi>Septuagint,</hi> when they quote the Scriptures of the old Teſtament, and yet that tranſlation had many variations in it from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, and haply more then our Engliſh tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath. The Apoſtle citing a place out of the Septuagint, where they expreſſe not the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:159980:39"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it is contained in <hi>Scripture,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 6. And there is no queſtion but the <hi>Helleniſts</hi> and <hi>weſtern Jewes</hi> ſcattered up and down in <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp;c. uſed the Greeke tranſlation of the Scriptures in their Synagogues, as appears by the confluence of the Greeks and Gentiles to them who underſtood not <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and yet they of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raea,</hi> a city <note n="a" place="margin">Plin. <hi>lib. 4. cap. 10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Stephanus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> are commended for ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the old Teſtament, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining of <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine by them: and in that ſearch there were <hi>Greeks</hi> that bare the <hi>Jews</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as appears, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 11, 12. And what Scriptures could they ſearch but <hi>the Scriptures of the Greeke Tranſlation;</hi> I could eaſily demonſtrate that the Scripture calls the originall tranſlated, <hi>ſcripture,</hi> &amp; not without juſt reaſon: for the Scripture ſtands not <hi>in cortice verborum</hi> but in <hi>medulla ſenſus,</hi> its the ſame wine in this veſſel w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was drawn out of that. Tranſlations are but veſſels or taps (as I may call them) to ſet Scriptures abroach; as for faults &amp; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in that tranſlation, if that argument be able to batter and make a breach, let it but have rope e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and it will make as great a breach in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, for when you come to find that ther are <hi>variae lectiones,</hi> and that in the Margent truer then that in the Text, as in that famous place <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in margine. <hi>Vide</hi> Foord <hi>in</hi> Pſalm 22.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 17. or ſhall queſtion the true pointing or printing of the originall, whither will not this wild argument run away with you, until you come to find the <hi>very ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal</hi> written by the Prophets own hand, or by the hand of ſome <hi>amanuenſis</hi> infallibly directed &amp; gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; The <hi>Scriptures expreſt in Engliſh are the word of God.</hi> The deficiency of exact tranſlation of this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:159980:39"/> or that particular <hi>word</hi> doth not invalidate the <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> or bodie of the Scriptures. But I ſhall not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceed in this chaſe; I have but a word or two left, and that is to exhort you to quicken up your zeale for God and his truth: ſearch out and remove the obſtructions that are in and amongſt your ſelves, whether <hi>private ends</hi> or <hi>State ends,</hi> or whatſoever they be. Let not <hi>Reformation</hi> and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be cryed up for deſigne, and to <hi>ſerve turnes;</hi> ſettle it ſpeedily. Send forth the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> that it may teſtifie to the world that you hold the <hi>forme</hi> of ſound and wholſome words: Let ſome governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and order be eſtabliſhed; <hi>religion</hi> is the <hi>ball of contention, many mens hopes</hi> lye in our <hi>differences,</hi> and their intereſts are ſerved upon them. We have profeſt enough for reformation and purity, and have covenanted to endeavour it. The <hi>world is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of words,</hi> they looke for fruit; Let this day ſet an edge upon you. No man take a <hi>breake-faſt</hi> of this <hi>faſt,</hi> let not our ruine be under your hand. There was a <hi>But</hi> in <hi>Naamans</hi> ſtory: he was ſuch and ſuch a man, <hi>but a Leper;</hi> You have done worthily, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted ſeriouſly: <hi>But</hi> the matter of Reformation lyes moſt of it as yet in the Covenant, and is but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle crept out of that ſhell; It may be the fooliſhneſs of many opinions on foot, makes you ſlight them, as <note n="a" place="margin">Calvin in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſc. de <hi>Serve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaid of <hi>Servetus</hi> his firſt onſet, <hi>ſecurum me reddidit ipſa dogmatum fatuitas:</hi> but be not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Socrates <hi>lib. 1.</hi> de Arrio.</note> a great fire may riſe out of a ſmall ſpark. Let the ſoules of ſo many thouſands of people be preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in your eyes, and the Lord make your name like the name of thoſe that have built the houſe of God; I pray you let mee not bee underſtood to ſhip
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:159980:40"/> in one and the ſame bottom every error or miſtake with damnable <hi>haereſies;</hi> ſome differences in opinion are as the ſtrivings (as <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>L. Verulam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Advancement of learning.</note> one elegantly ſaith) of one Iſraelite with another: and theſe <hi>Moſes</hi> quiets and parts them fairely, and ſome (namely haereſies figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the very foundation) are like the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> ſtriving with the <hi>Iſraelite</hi> whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmites down. There muſt be differences made between <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> and <hi>haereſie, erroneous</hi> and <hi>Hereticks, ſeducers</hi> and <hi>ſeduced,</hi> I would I might intreat, nay preſſe it upon thoſe that are called pure <hi>Independents,</hi> that they would zealouſly and ſincerely declare againſt the doctrinall errours and haereſies of theſe dayes, that ſuch pernicious opinions may not ſhelter themſelves under their name or wing, nor ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny indulgence or toleration be either deſired or granted upon ſuch a reaſon, as all may come in at the ſame breach or port, for that would bee but a ſelling of the Church into a <hi>liberty</hi> of being in <hi>cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity</hi> to <hi>deſtructive confuſions and errours.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 11. lin. 5. for</hi> deat r. doceat. <hi>P. 30. l. 15. for</hi> ſigmenta r. figmenta. <hi>p. 43. l. 30 for</hi> becauſe r. being. <hi>p. 45. l. 29. for</hi> formerly <hi>r.</hi> fermally.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:40"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:41"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Jovis,</hi> 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Martij. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament that Mr. <hi>Rows</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gewen</hi> doe from this Houſe give thankes unto Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> for the great paines they tooke in their Sermons prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on the 10. <hi>Martij,</hi> 1646. at <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> Weſtminſter before the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, being a day of publique Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the growth of Errours, Haereſies, &amp;c. And they are to deſire them to print their Sermons, wherein they are to have the like priviledge in printing of them, as others in the like kinde uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſinge. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint <hi>Abel Roper</hi> to Print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICHARD VINES.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:159980:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
